<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hereafter foloweth the knowledge, properties, and the vertues of herbes.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1540</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07743</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 180867233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13175.6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S92946</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">180867233</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 180867233</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07743)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191753)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2286:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hereafter foloweth the knowledge, properties, and the vertues of herbes.</title>
                  <author>Wyer, Robert, fl. 1530-1556, printer.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[120] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me Robert Wyer, dwellynge in saynt Martyns parysshe, at the sygne of saynt Iohn Euangelyst, besyde Charynge Crosse.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1540?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; date from STC (2nd ed.)..</note>
                  <note>Title page ornaments; initials; printer's device (McK. 69) at colop.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-P⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Herbals --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicinal plants --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Botany, Medical --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191753:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191753:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191753:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191753:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ Hereafter folo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, proper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, and the vertues of Herbes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:191753:3"/>
            <head>¶ Of the knowledge &amp; vertues of herbes, and the fyrſte letter begyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth with .A.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Agnus caſtus.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Gnus caſtus is a herbe that men call Tutſayne or Parke leues, &amp; it hath leues ſomdele red: lyke to the leues of Orage, &amp; it hath ſygnes in his leues, as it were leues of Plantayne, and he hath yelow flowers as great as a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and this herbe beryth aboue at the crope blacke beryes when they ben rype, &amp; yf they be not rype they ben yelowe as the flower of it is. And this herbe groweth moche in woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; in drye grounde. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is, that he wyll kepe man and woman chaſte, for as Dracolidon and Placius ſayth that this herbe is called Agnꝰ caſtus for this ſkyl, for the vſe and the ſauour therof maketh men chaſte. Alſo he wyl open the poores, and let out wycked humours, &amp; ſpyces of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. This herbe diſtroyeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moyſture of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſede. Alſo Authours ſeyne, let this herbe be well ſod with fenell ſede, and a lytel eyſell is good to dyſtroy colde dropſy. Alſo let hym be ſod with Smalledge and Sauge in ſalte water, and than waſſhe the hynder partye of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes heade, he helpeth an euyll that men
<pb facs="tcp:191753:3"/> calle Litargia. Alſo this diſtroyeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fowle luſt of lecherye and it be dronke, but men vſe to lay it on them ſlepyng. And therfore ſome men eate this herbe roſted, for yf men eate it rawe he wyl lyghtly ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre heade ache. This herbe is good to dyſtroy the hardnes and the ſtoppyng of the lyuer, and of the mylt. Alſo a playſter of this herbe is good to do awaye the ache of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes heade that is gendred of wicked humours, this herbe is hote and drye and there be thre ſpyces of her. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Apium.</head>
               <p>APium is an herbe men call Smaledge or Marche, this herbe hath leues lyke to Louage: but the leues be not ſo longe, alſo it is not ſo ſtronge of ſauour as Louage, and it hath ſede as it were Percely, and it is lyke to Percely ſede. ¶ The vertue of hym is that he wyl make a man to make water, and this herbe openeth the ſtoppynge of the lyuer. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ſede therof hardeth a mannes wombe. Alſo the propertye of hym is to drawe all the wycked humours of the body vnto the heade and to the ſtomacke, &amp; the wombe, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is forbode to women that be with chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, or that kepeth ſuckynge chyldren to eate of this herbe leſte they be mad, and take ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the fallynge euyll. This herbe is hote and
<pb facs="tcp:191753:4"/> drye, and hath fyue ſpyces of her. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Auetum.</head>
               <p>AVetu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an herbe that is called Auete otherwyſe Dyll, this hath leues lyke to Fenel, and the ſame ſauour and bereth her ſede as Fenell, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſede of this is ſomwhat brode as the ſede of Orage. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyl make a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pyſſe. Alſo he ſwageth the ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bulling &amp; the wycked wynde in a mans wombe. Alſo it diſtroyeth the poxe, &amp; yf the ſede of this herbe be brende and ſtrawed vpon a wounde it heleth ſoone that wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and namely yf a man be ſcalded on his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres, or on his yerde, it ſhall be hole in the ſame maner. Alſo a playſter made of this herbe, and layde to the Emerawdes he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them ſoone, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Apumeriſus.</head>
               <p>APumeriſus is an herbe called Cerfoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le or Cheruyle, this herbe hath ſmale leues lyke to the leues of Hemeloke, but this herbe is good in ſauoure, and hath a whyte flower &amp; longe ſede lyke to otes. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is yf that he be dronke with wyne it ſhall make a man well to make water. Alſo he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuereth of the reynes &amp; of the bladder, and yf he be dronke with wyne, he letteth out and vnbyndeth the wycked wynde fro the ſydes
<pb facs="tcp:191753:4"/> and the ſtoppynge of the wombe, and of the lyuer, and of all other woundes, &amp; this herbe withholdeth caſtynge. Alſo a playſter made of the herbe &amp; tempered with eyſell diſtroyeth wylde fyre, and heleth the canker, this herbe is one of the ſpyces of Smaledge, it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Abſinthium.</head>
               <p>ABſinthium is an herbe that men call worm woode, this herbe hath leues as Mugworte, and the leues be ſomdele whyte vnder, and he hath a great more, and of the more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out many brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches, and bereth flowers as Mugworte. ¶ The vertue therof is to comforte the ſtomacke and clenſeth the herte. Galien ſayeth that yf this herbe be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to an euyl, of the whiche euyl the matter is not fully defyed it ſhal harde the ſtomacke and let the digeſtyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and yf the matter of the euyl be ryped, the herbe ſhal make a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfe. This herbe is to put away dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, alſo yf this herbe be dronke with ſpiconarde, it ſwageth the ache of the ſtomacke &amp; of the wombe. Alſo yf this herbe be tempred with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and dronke, it heleth the ſwellyng of a mans mouth, &amp; putteth away the blackenes by a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes iye, and clereth the iyen. Alſo yf the ioyce of this herbe be ſtylled in to a mans
<pb facs="tcp:191753:5"/> noſtrylles, it dryeth vp the moyſture that ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth out of hym. Alſo it kepeth clothes from mothes and thou put it in thy preſſe, alſo it kepeth bokes from eatynge of wormes, this herbe is drye and hote &amp; hath two ſpyces.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Archemeſia.</head>
               <p>ARchemeſia is an herbe that men call Mugworte, it is lyke to wormewood in leues, but they be not fully ſo rounde, and it hath a longer ſtalke, and many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge out of one, &amp; it bereth flowers as doth worm<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wood. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take a Iourney, and beareth this herbe with hym, he ſhal not be wery ne haue no trauayle in his waye, alſo yf this herbe be in a houſe, there ſhall no wycked ſpyryte dwell there, Alſo this herbe puned with talowe helpeth the akynge and ſorenes of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes fete, alſo the powder of this herbe dronke with luke warme water helpeth the akynge of a mans guttes, it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Affodillus.</head>
               <p>AFfodillus is an herbe that men calleth Affadyll lyke to leke, and he hath ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe flowers, and at the top he hath rounde coddes, when the flowers be fallynge they hath ſede lyke to an oynyon. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> braunches of this herbe
<pb facs="tcp:191753:5"/> is good to hele the dropſy. Alſo the flowers therof dronke with wyne, it heleth the bytyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of venymous wormes. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce with the more with a lytell myrre, and a lytell ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheron ſodde and medled with ſwete wyne and ſtrayned, it heleth re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge iyen, alſo the moore therof burned in to powder put in to iyen that haue loſt her heer ſhall make heer to growe, &amp; alſo a harde ſharpe clothe be wette in the ioyce of this herbe, and therwith the morfewe or a place that moche bowe is, be anoynted with the cloth in the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fewe and the bowe ſhal fal away, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Aſtrologia longa.</head>
               <p>AStrologia longa is an herbe called Mader, it hath leues lyke to Mader, &amp; hath a braunche the lengthe of a cubyte, and many braunches co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge out of the more, the braunches of this herbe hath many knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ryght as hath Mader, &amp; ſom what whyte flowers. ¶ The vertue is it wyll vnbynde the ſtoppyng of the lyuer, &amp; let paſſe wycked wyndes. Alſo yf this herbe be dronke with wyne he purgeth venym in a mans body, or without in the veynes, wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, that be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge. This herbe is hote and drye, and ſhal be gathered in harueſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:6"/>
               <head>¶ Abrotanum.</head>
               <p>ABrotanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an herbe that men calleth Sothernwoode, and this herbe hath a ſtalke as it were rewe, and ſo he is brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched, ſaue this herbe hath ſtrayter leues then hath Rewe. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that yf the ſede therof be broken and dronken with water it helpeth the men that hath the ſtone, and the palſey, &amp; yf the herbe be dronke with wyne it helpeth hym that is bitten with any venymous wormes. Alſo the powder of this herbe breaketh harde poſtumes. Alſo yf this herbe be brent, and the aſſhes be medled with olde Oyle, and put to the place where lacked heer, and it ſhall growe agayne, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Ariſtologia rotunda.</head>
               <p>ARiſtologia rotu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da is an herbe that is called Aſtrologe or Galyngale, this herbe hath leues lyke to a purſe, and hath but one branche and grene leues aboue, &amp; vnder ben whyte, and it flowreth as it were betayn ſaue the flowers ben whyte. ¶ The vertue as ypocras ſayeth is, yf that he be dronken with hote water, it is medycynable for men that ben ſtopped in the breſt, &amp; for the fallyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge euyll, and for the potagre, this herbe is hote &amp; drye, and ſhall be gathered in harueſt,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:6"/> and this is a ſpyce of red mader.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Ameos.</head>
               <p>AMeos is an herbe called Amee, this hath leues lyke to Elderne, but they ben leſſe and a longe braunche and flowreth, and ſedeth as it were perſely, and the ſede is lyke to the ſede of Perſely. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is yf it be dronke with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny it ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wormes in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wombe, and vnbyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth great ſtoppynge of wycked wyndes in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wombe, he breketh the ſtone, he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſtomacke yf it be colde, he clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the lyuer and the reynes and wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, he helpeth the bytynge of venymous beeſtes, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Alleluya.</head>
               <p>ALleluya is a herbe called woodſore or ſtubworte, this herbe hath .iii. leues of the whiche .ii. ben rownde and a lytell depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboue and it hath a whyte flower, but no longe ſtalke. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is yf it be roſted vpon the coles in leues of the red docke, then he ſhall frete away deade fleſſhe, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Agrimonia.</head>
               <p>AGrimonia is an herbe called Egrimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye, and the leues be lyke to Tanſey, but the leues of this ben greatter, and he hath
<pb facs="tcp:191753:7"/> a blewe flower, and when the flower is fall he hath ſede that wyll hange in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, this groweth by dyches, or hedges, and woodes. ¶ The vertue is yf he be eten grene with the rote he heleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> akynge of the wom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be. Alſo this herbe tempered with eyſyl wyll heale a ſore hurted with yron. Alſo yf it be vſed in meates it wyll hele the ſorenes of the mylte, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Auancia.</head>
               <p>AVancia is an herbe called Auendre, it hath leues lyke to an hare foote, this herbe is called harefote, and he hath a yelowe flower as it were Turmentyll. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is yf he be dryed &amp; made in powder, and put in a lytel wyne or hote water and gyuen to a man that hath the Feuers to drynke, it ſhall helpe hym ſoone. Alſo it helpeth moche woundes, and the canker yf it be dronke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Altea.</head>
               <p>ALtea is an herbe called the Holyhocke or wylde malowe, it hath leues as it were malowe and hath a longe braunche, he ſedeth as doth malowe. ¶ The vertue is yf it be ſhreded with telow, and taken to a man that hath the potagre, he ſhall be hole within thre dayes. Alſo yf this herbe be ſoden with vynegre and with lynſede, and layde vnto a
<pb facs="tcp:191753:7"/> mans ſydes it departeth wycked gatheryng that ben gendred togyther in a mans body it groweth in feldes and hote places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Amariſta.</head>
               <p>AMariſta is an herbe called Mawthen or docter fenel, this herbe is moch lyke to Camamyll, and flowreth as Camamyll, for it hath whyte flowers, &amp; this herbe ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as it groweth in the felde, and in corne. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that the ioyce therof dronke is good for the canker. Alſo to hele the pypes of the Emerawdes and there be two ſpyces of the herbe, one hath a whyte flower, the other a yelowe flower.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Aniſum.</head>
               <p>ANiſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an herbe called Annies, it hath leues as Comen or Fenel, but the ſede is more than Fenell ſede. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he vnbyndeth wicked wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des and great humours, and he openeth the ſtoppynge of the lyuer. Alſo he maketh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes mylke to wax. Alſo he ſtyrreth man and woman to workes of kynde. Alſo it ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth a man to make water &amp; to ſwete. Alſo it maketh the wombe harde yf it be laxe, this herbe or elles the ſede ſhulde be take moyſte, and roſted or perched in maner of medycyne this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:8"/>
               <head>¶ Alleum.</head>
               <p>ALleu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an herbe called Garlyke, this herbe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men. ¶ The vertue of hym is that he wyll vnbynde all great ſtoppyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and wycked wyndes in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes bodye. Alſo he helpeth a man to make water, but neuertheleſſe he greueth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes iyen for the great vnbyndyng and drawyng that he ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuouſly draweth the ſyght. Alſo he dyſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a venym within a man. Alſo he healeth colde ſores as it were Tryacle. Alſo he doth a way the morfewe of bladders in what pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that they ben of the bodye yf it be well rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed therwith, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Aſtarton.</head>
               <p>AStarton is an herbe called Lunarye, this herbe groweth amonge ſtones or hye places, this herbe ſhyneth by nyght, this herbe hath his moyſture yfounde by ſhepher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in the felde, and it hath yelowe flowers hole and rownde as cokobell, or flowers of Floxgloue, the leues of this herbe ben zende blewe, &amp; they haue the marcke of the Moone in the myddes as it were .iii. leued graſſe, and the leues ben more then .iii. leued graſſe, and ben rownde as a peny, it hath a ſtalke &amp; that is red, it ſmelleth as it were Muſke, and the ioyce is yelowe, this groweth in the newe with
<pb facs="tcp:191753:8"/> Moone without leues, &amp; euery day waxeth a newe lefe .xv. dayes, and after .xv. dayes he leſeth a lefe as the Moone wexeth and way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and where ſoeuer this herbe be he gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in great qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyte. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that who ſo eteth his bayns or els of the herbe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waynynge of the Moone whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is in ſigno virginis, yf he haue the fallyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge euyll he ſhallbe hole. Alſo who ſo hath the fallyng euyll bere this herbe aboute his necke and he ſhalbe hole. And it hath many mo ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tues than I can tell at this tyme.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .ii. letter begynneth with .B.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Betonia.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Etonia is an herbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Betayne or byſchope pyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worte, this herbe hath hole leues, but they be ende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by the ſydes without, &amp; it hath a red flower in the croppe of the ſtalke. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is yf he be pune and put to the wounde in the heade that is ſmytten with a ſtroke, he ſhall hele the wounde fayre and well, and the better yf it be freſſhe. Alſo this herbe wyll drawe out broken bones of wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des as ſome Auctours ſayen. Alſo take the water of Betayne, or els breke the leues
<pb facs="tcp:191753:9"/> and take the ioyce and put it in to thyne iyes, than ſhall you fynde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is is good for akyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge or ſorenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iyen. Alſo take of Betayn a dragma and pune it and medle it with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that is warme, and drynke it .iiii. tymes faſtynge and it wyll breke the webbe aboute the iyen, and clenſe theym well &amp; fayre. Alſo yf thou haue waterynge iyen eate euery day a lytel Betayne and it clenſeth them. Alſo yf thou haue akynge iyen, take the leues of Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne freſſhe by them ſelfe, or els with a lytel water, and then wrynge out the ioyce, &amp; put therto a lytell roſe water, warme them well to gyther, and ſtyl it in to thyne iyen, and af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terwarde put aboue wolle, and ſo thou ſhalt be hole. Alſo yf thou blede moche at the noſe take Betayne and pune it with a lytell ſalte, and do it to thyne noſethyrlles, as moche as thou mayeſt with thy thombe and thy medle fynger, and than holde thy noſethyrlle with the ſame fyngers, and the bſode ſhall ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che. Alſo yf thou haue ſore tethe, take Betayne and ſeth it in olde wyne, or in eyfyll tyl it be ſodde to the thyrde parte, and holde it in thy mouth, and thou ſhalt amende. Alſo yf thou haue the cowghe take two ou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of Betayne and a lytell ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and ſeth it with eſy fyre, and vſe it .ix. dayes. Alſo yf a
<pb facs="tcp:191753:9"/> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes yarde be ſwollen or els ſore, take Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne &amp; pune it with lytell wyne, and after laye to the yarde and he ſhallbe hole. Alſo yf a man may not holde his mete within hym, take .iiii. dragmes of the powder of Betayn and medle it with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny that is ſodde, &amp; make pellettes as great as a walſche note, &amp; gyue hym .iiii. dayes eche day a pellet, and do hym to drynke .ii. ſponefull of that water, &amp; than he ſhall be hole. Alſo yf a man be potagre, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke Betayne and pune it &amp; lay it to his feete, and he ſhall be ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. Alſo take a lytel Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne or the powder and eate it erely, and it ſhall helpe the fro dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes that day, theſe medycynes ben proued. This herbe groweth in woodes and holly places amonge buſſhes in derke places, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Balſaminta.</head>
               <p>BAlſaminta is an herbe that men cal hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemynt, this herbe hath leues lyke vnto other myntes, and ſome men calleth it water mynt, it groweth moche by the water, but it hath a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger ſauer then hath another mynt. ¶ The vertue is that he wyll co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, &amp; make a man wel to defy his meate. Alſo this herbe purgeth a man within the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye, and maketh hym well to ſpeke. Alſo the ioyce of this herbe medled with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and a
<pb facs="tcp:191753:10"/> lytel wyne doth away the ſchylke of a mans ſtomacke, and other wicked wyndes of hym. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of this herbe dronke with wyne yſode maketh a woman with chylde eſely to bere her chylde, &amp; ſoone to be delyuered, this is hote and drye, and hath two ſpyces.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Beta.</head>
               <p>BEta is an herbe called Bete, this herbe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men, and groweth in Gardaynes, and there be two ſpyces therof, and Diacoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſayeth, one is whyte another blacke.</p>
               <p>¶ The vertue of this herbe is that the ioyce of this herbe putte it in to the noſethyrlles, it clenſeth a mans heed. Alſo this herbe ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the akynge of a mans heed. Alſo it clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the heed from nyttes, and from other ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myn. Alſo it repayreth &amp; kepeth the heer of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes heed. Alſo this herbe dyſtroyeth bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and byles. Alſo Diacolides ſayeth, that vpon the rote of this herbe maye be planted a graffe that wyll afterwarde beare fruyte, as vpon the cole rote.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Borago domeſtices.</head>
               <p>BOrago Domeſtices is an herbe called Borage, this groweth in Gardaynes, and he hath ſhorte leues and a blewe flower. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wil clenſe the red colour of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo this herbe medled
<pb facs="tcp:191753:10"/> with wyne maketh a man glade and mery, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Bigula.</head>
               <p>BIgula is an herbe called Brome Bugle this hath leues ſom what rounde, and ſom what tournynge to blacke, and he hath a blew flower and ſomwhat boyſtous. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyl hele woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des in a mans heade. Alſo it breketh and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth the rewme in a mans heade and the akynge, he groweth in woodes, and he is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and drye, and there ben .ii. ſpyces of hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Burneta.</head>
               <p>BVrneta is an herbe called Burnet, &amp; it hath a blewe flower as hath Hayhoue, and leues lyke to Tanſey, but they be not ſo great. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll diſtroy the great humours and the laxa tyue within a man. Alſo he healeth and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſtoppynge of the lyuer, and maketh a man to pyſſe. Alſo he healeth a man of the yelow euyll. Alſo the ioyce medled with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and dronke, vnbyndeth &amp; healeth the ſore of the rybbes and pappes, and there be .ii. ſpy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of this herbe one groweth in harde lande and hath lytell leues, another groweth in me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dowes and haue more leues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Burſa paſtoris.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:11"/>
               <p>BUrſa paſtoris is an herbe called ſhepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des purs or tocheworte, this hath leues departed ſomdele as Burnet, &amp; hath a why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te flower, and when he hath loſt his flower, he hath the maner of a purs, in the whiche is ſede. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is he wyll ſoone ſtaunche blode yf he be dronke, it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in feldes and gardaynes wel nyghe al aboute, and he is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .iii. letter begynneth with .C.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Camamilla.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Amamilla is an herbe cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Camamyl, this herbe hath leues lyke to the mauthe and white flowers but he ſmelleth ſote, &amp; the maw the ſtynketh.</p>
               <p>¶ The vertue is yf he be dronke with wyne he breketh the ſtone. Alſo he ſtroyeth the ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe euyll. Alſo he healeth the akynge of the lyuer. Alſo yf he be chewed he heleth the ſore of the mouth, this is hote and drye, and gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth moſte in gardaynes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Calamintum.</head>
               <p>CAlamintum is an herbe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is called Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamynt, this herbe hath leues lyke vnto Mynt, but the leues ben whyter and rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der then the leues of Mynt, and more ſtronger of
<pb facs="tcp:191753:11"/> ſauour, &amp; it hath a whyte ſtalke. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this herbe is that he wyl diſtroy a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes talent as ypocras ſayth, and there be thre ſpices of this herbe, one that is ſtony, another that is hery, another that is waterye, &amp; they be hote and drye, and he that is hery maketh a man moyſte, he that is ſtony yf he be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke he maketh a man that hath dronke venym hole. Alſo this herbe made in playſter &amp; layde to any venymous ſore, it draweth the venym fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within outwarde. Alſo who ſo drynketh this herbe .iii. dayes, it heleth the yelow euyl, he that is herye it helpeth from the lepour, the ioyce of this herbe put in to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes eares, it kylleth the wormes therin, it comforteth the ſtomacke and helpeth to defye, and it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draweth caſtynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Craſſula maior.</head>
               <p>CRaſſula maior, is an herbe called Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyn or Ormale, this herbe hath ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what thycke leues as it were Peny worte.</p>
               <p>¶ The vertue of this herbe is yf it be layde to a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, he ſhal hele it without any helpe, this herbe groweth in gardaynes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Craſſula minor.</head>
               <p>CRaſſula minor is an herbe called Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor or Stonecrope, it hath lytell leues lyke to Orpin, and it groweth vpon howſes
<pb facs="tcp:191753:12"/> and walles &amp; groweth ſomwhat hangynge. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is, he wyll make a man to lyue chaſte, &amp; is dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke for the ague.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Cituca.</head>
               <p>CItuca is an herbe called Hembloke or herbe Benet, it hath leues lyke to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely, and ſo he flowreth &amp; ſedeth as doth Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely, but this herbe ſtynketh. ¶ The vertue is he kepeth may dens pappes from great wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge. Alſo yf the ioyce of this herbe be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke he diſtroyeth the great appetite of lechery. Alſo the ioyce of this with the ſpume of ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and ſwynes grece diſtroyeth the hote po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagre, and ſwageth the ſwellyng, this herbe is colde and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Centuaria maior.</head>
               <p>CEntuaria maior is an herbe that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth the more centory or earth gell, this hath leues lyke to the leſſe ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tory, but they be more whyter, and hath a ſtalke and yelowe flowers, and flowreth not but in the topps. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is yf it be ſodden with good wyne &amp; gyuen a man to drynke, it healeth the ſyckenes of the lyuer. Alſo this herbe ſodden in wyne and dronke, dryeth vp wylde humours of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes mylt, this hath ben often proued. Alſo the ioyce of this herbe ſodden in water is good to hele a wounde of
<pb facs="tcp:191753:12"/> another place that is ſmytten with a canker yf he be anoynted therwith, it is hote &amp; drye, and groweth in drye grounde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Centuaria minor.</head>
               <p>CEntuaria minor is an herbe called the leſſe Centory or criſtus lader, this hath leues lyke to the more Centory, but the leues ben more grener, and he hath thre braunches co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge out of the more, &amp; the flower ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what red. ¶ The vertue is yf the powder or the ioyce be medled with olde wyne &amp; drynke is good to hele the ſtyngynge of an adder, or any other venymous beeſt. Alſo yf you haue ſore iyen, take the ioyce &amp; anoynte your iyen &amp; thou ſhalte be hole. Alſo yf thou haue any venym within the, take and pune this herbe and tempre it with Ayſell and drynke it and you ſhall caſt vp all the venym, &amp; it groweth in drye places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Carin.</head>
               <p>CArin is a herbe called caraway, it hath leues lyke ſomwhat to Fenell, &amp; a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſtalke and rounde ſede, more then the ſede of Perſely. ¶ The vertue of hym is that he dyſtroyeth wycked wyndes and the coughe, and heleth men that hath the frenſy, and by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng with venymous beeſtes. Alſo this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be medled with ayſelheleth ſcabbes &amp; tetters,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:13"/> and reſtoreth heer there it falleth away, this herbe is hote &amp; dry, &amp; groweth in gardaynes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Celodonia.</head>
               <p>CElodonia is an herbe called Celondyn or Deten wort, this hath leues that ben grene and yelowe flowers, and when he is broke he droppeth mylke, &amp; the leues be ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what lyke to Columbyne. ¶ The vertue of this herbe as Plinius ſayeth, yf a ſwalowes byrde be hurte the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fetcheth of this herbe and healeth hym agayne. Alſo it healeth the ache of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tethe. Alſo it elenſeth a mans heed. Alſo it healeth the canker and other ſores in the month, this is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Cidamu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</head>
               <p>CIdamu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an herbe called Hertnote, or Dylnote, or Flete, or Haleworte, this hath leues lyke to Fenel, and whyte flowers and ſmall ſtalkes, &amp; groweth in woodes and medowes. ¶ The vertue is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll fetche awaye deade fleſſhe. Alſo this herbe put on a fore, or on a place that lacked heer, it heleth it and reſtoreth heer, this is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Caulis.</head>
               <p>CAulis is an herbe called Coleworte, this herbe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men to you. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of hym is that he wyl clenſe freſſhe wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and the canker, &amp; hele ſore iyen that haue
<pb facs="tcp:191753:13"/> almoſte loſt theyr ſyghte. Alſo it maketh wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mans mylke to waxe, and he comforteth the ſtomacke. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of this herbe tempred with alym &amp; eyſell ſwageth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lepre. Alſo it is good for dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kenes, &amp; groweth in gardaynes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Coriandrum.</head>
               <p>COriandrum is an herbe called Cetrian<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, he hath leues lyke to erthenote ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dele, &amp; hath a lytel whyte flower &amp; rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſede ſomwhat whyte, &amp; he is ſtronger in ſauour. ¶ The vertue is yf the ioyce be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with honnye, it ſleeth all the wormes in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes body, &amp; alſo hardeth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wombe. Alſo yf the ſede of this herbe be ete it driueth away the Feuers that come the thyrde daye, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Capillus veneris.</head>
               <p>CApillus veneris is called mayden heer or water wortes, this hath leues like to Ferne, but the leues ben ſmall, and groweth vpon ſtones and walles, and in the myddle of the leues is as it were a blacke heer. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll breke the ſtone. Alſo yf it be dronke with wyne it dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth the venym, he is colde and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Crocus.</head>
               <p>CRocus is an herbe called Saffron, this hath lytell leues as it were graſſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:191753:14"/> blewe flowers. ¶ The vertue of hym is that he wyl dyſtroy all maner of abhomynacyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomacke. Alſo he maketh a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſlepe. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flower is good for many medicyns, and namely for cokes co colour theyr potage and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Centinodium.</head>
               <p>CEntinodium is an herbe called Centi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodi or ſwyngraſſe, this herbe groweth welnye ouer all. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll breke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone, this herbe is hote &amp; dry, &amp; may be gathered at all tymes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Caprifolium.</head>
               <p>CAprifoliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is an herbe called woodbyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de or withwynde, this groweth in hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or in woodes, and it wyll beclyp a tre in her growynge, as doth yuye, and hath white flowers. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyl hele cankers, and woundes, and blanders, and akynge of the teth, and ſores in a mans toen. Alſo it is good to hele ſwellyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſmyt with venym, this is hote &amp; drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Canabaria.</head>
               <p>CAnabaria is an herbe called wylde hem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe, this hath leues lyke to hempe.</p>
               <p>¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he is good for the Feuer, and groweth moche by water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:14"/>
               <head>¶ Coſtus.</head>
               <p>COſtus is an herbe called Coſte or leſſe Detayne, this hath leues as Detayne, but they be not ſo moche, and the leues be more whyter then the leues of Detayne. Alſo it is ſote in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he heleth the ſyckenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breſt and of the longes, &amp; alſo he wyll breke the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume. Alſo he draweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> humours of mans iyen. Alſo he is good for the ſtomacke, and this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Cepe.</head>
               <p>CEpe is an herbe called a Onyon, this is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men ynowe. ¶ The vertue of this is that he wyll greatly comforte the ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macke. Alſo he neſſheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wombe. Alſo this herbe with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and eyſell, &amp; dronke is good to hell the bytyng of a mad dogge. Alſo this herbe medled with womans mylke heleth the akyng of eeren. Alſo the ioyce of this dronke with any lycour, is good for a man that hath ſoft ſodeynly his ſpeche. Alſo the ioyce put to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes noſethyrlſes breketh out the rewme or any other wycked ſtoppynge, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Columbina.</head>
               <p>COlumbina is an herbe called Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bayne or Tockefote, or Coluerfote, or
<pb facs="tcp:191753:15"/> Sawnardes, this herbe hath leues ſomwhat lyke to Ceſidony, but he droppeth no mylke. ¶ The vertue is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is good for a man that hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quinſy, &amp; ſhuld be gathered in auguſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Cominum.</head>
               <p>COminum is an herbe Called Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn, this hath leues lyke to Coryandre, and he hath many braunches co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge out of the ſtalke, and he hath a ſtronge ſauoure. ¶ The vertue is that he dyſtroyeth wycked wyndes and other euylles of the ſtomacke. Alſo he helpeth a man to make water, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Cardiaca.</head>
               <p>CArdiaca is an herbe called Cardyake, or Aſſper, this herbe hath leues ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what lyke to blynde nettell, &amp; he pryc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſomwhat vpon the tongue, and he hath lytell coddes &amp; therin his ſede is. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is that he is good for men that hath the fallynge euyll. Alſo he is good for ſauces.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Ciſera.</head>
               <p>CIſera is an herbe called Frenche peyſe he hath leues lyke a more payſe, &amp; alſo coddes, he hath not ſo great leues, nor ſo lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge coddes as hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other peyſe, &amp; he hath ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of her whyte &amp; red, &amp; he groweth in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynes, &amp; her ſede in ſchaps as it were a peyſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:15"/>
               <head>¶ Camelion.</head>
               <p>CAmelion is an herbe called woſueſtheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell or a whyte the ſtell, this herbe hath whyte leues great and brode, and hath a red flower and groweth in wayes. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this herbe is great, that yf ye take this herbe when the ſonne is in Caprycorne with the new moone, yf ye bere it with the, or vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the there ſhall no myſchefe fall on the.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Conſolida maior.</head>
               <p>COnſolida maior is an herbe called con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fery, this hath leues lyke to horſhelme but they be not ſo whyte, &amp; groweth in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery places, and hath two ſpyces on her, the one hath a whyte flower, the other a red, and lyke they ben of one vertue. ¶ The vertue is yf a man be broſed within hym or broke, take the rote of this herbe, &amp; roſt hym well amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge aſſhes, and take hym to the ſicke faſtynge with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and let hym eate it and he ſhal be hole. Alſo this herbe hath broken ſeues, and he is hote &amp; moyſte, and bereth blacke ſede.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Conſolida minor.</head>
               <p>COnſolida minor is called Dayſye or Browſwort, and he hath leues lyke to the leſſe centory and a whyte flower. ¶ The vertue is that he is good to breke botches, yf he be puned and layde therto, this is a ſpyce
<pb facs="tcp:191753:16"/> of Confery, and he groweth welny ouer all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Conſolida media.</head>
               <p>COnſolida media is called whyte Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyn or whyte Goldes, this herbe hath leues ſomwhat longe, and they ben entended a lytell without, &amp; hath a whyte flower that is ſom what lyke to dayſe, and it groweth in medowes and lees.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .iiii. letter begynneth with .D.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Dragancia.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Raga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia is an herbe called Dragance or El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwort or Cerpentyne, this herbe hath .iii. leues in eche brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che, and they be ſom what ſharp as an nedder. ¶ The vertue is and he be puned with wyne he putteth away all maner of venym. Alſo he healeth akynge of earen, and they be anoynted therwith. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo yf the powder of this herbe be blowne in a mans noſe, it clenſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noſe from re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng. Alſo it is good to diſtroy the gowte, and the canker, and the feſterynge of woundes, this herbe groweth in woodes and hylles, and he is hote and moyſte, and muſt be gathered in the moneth of Iune and Iuly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:16"/>
               <head>¶ Diptanum.</head>
               <p>DIptanum is called Detayne or detan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre, this herbe hath leues lyke to Coſte but they be grener than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leues of Coſte, and it hath a lytel whyte flower. ¶ The vertue is yf a woman be with a deed body it wyl dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer her therof, this herbe wyll drawe out an thorne, or yron out of a mans foote, or other places, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Daucus aſinius.</head>
               <p>DAucus aſinius is an herbe called birdeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt or Tanke, this herbe hath leues ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to Hemlocke, and hath a whyte flower. ¶ The vertue is that he is good to hele the dropſey and bytynge of venymous beeſtes. Alſo he openeth the ſtoppynge of the leuer, and of the mylt. Alſo he vubyndeth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes wombe, and maketh hym laxatyue, this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be groweth in feldes, and beareth his flower lyke to a byrdesneſte, and this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Daucus creticus.</head>
               <p>DAucus creticus is an herbe called the leſſe tanke, this hath leues lyke to wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Popy, but the leues ben more whyter, and he hath a flower that is purpull coloure, this groweth in wete, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Dens leonis.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:17"/>
               <p>DEns leonis is an herbe called daunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyon or lyons toth, this hath leues lyke to houndeſtoth, and he hath a yelow flower, and he hath no braunche but as eche flower ſpryngeth out of the more with a lytell brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and it droppeth mylke whan it is broke. ¶ The vertue is that the moore of it is good to hele the Feuer cotydyan, and it be dronke with wyne, it groweth all aboute.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Dragancia faminea.</head>
               <p>DRagancia feminea is an herbe called Dragaunce female, it hath leues lyke to yuy, but they haue whyte ſpeckes, and it hath a yelow ſtalke the length of two cubytz, other whyle as it were a croked ſtaf, and lyke to a ſnake, and ſhe beareth her ſede as it were a cluſter of grapes, and when the ſede is ripe it is yelowe, this herbe groweth in darke pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces. ¶ The vertue of this is that yf the ſede therof be puned with oyle and put to a mans iyen, it healeth the akynge of iyen. Alſo the ioyce of this herbe with a lytell wolle put to the noſethyrle, clenſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noſe from all fylth. Alſo the rote of this herbe puned with white wyne and ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny heleth all woundes, and the canker aryſed in. Alſo he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> froteth his hande well with the rote of this herbe, he may take edders without any parell. Alſo the ioyce of
<pb facs="tcp:191753:17"/> this rote dyſtroyeth the darkenes of the iyen, yf they be anoynted therwith. Alſo yf this herbe be dronke with wyne, he ſterith a man vnto lechery.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .v. letter begynneth with .E.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Elena campana.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Lena ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pana is an herbe called Enule ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>payne or horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eldron, this herbe hath leues as it were Comfery, but they be more whyter then the leues of Comfery, and he hath a longe ſtalke and a yelow flower. ¶ The vertue is yf a man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue waggynge teth and ete therof faſtynge, it wyll faſtyn his tethe. Alſo yf a man drynke this herbe it healeth hym from the ſtone, and helpeth hym to make water. Alſo yf it be dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke, it delyuereth a woman of a deade chylde. Alſo it hardyneth a mannes wombe yf it be laxatyue, this herbe heleth a man of the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe this herbe is hote and moyſte, it groweth in woodes and feldes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Endiua.</head>
               <p>ENdiua is an herbe called endyfe or horſe theſtyll, this herbe hath leues lyke ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyſtel, this hath pykes in the rygge and a ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe flower. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is
<pb facs="tcp:191753:18"/> thet the ioyce therof medled with hote water, and dronke heleth the ſtoppynge of the mylt and of the lyuer. Alſo it is good to hele the ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe euyll, and the feuer tercyan, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te poſtume. Alſo this herbe ſwageth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great hete of the lyuer, and of the ſtomacke, and it is colde and moyſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Eruca.</head>
               <p>ERuca is an herbe called ſkyrwhyte, this hath leues lyke to bylre, but they be not ſo longe, and it hath a great rote. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is that the ioyce of the leues wronge out, holde in a mans mouth heleth all the ſorenes of the mouth. Alſo it breketh the ſtone. Alſo the ioyce of this herbe ſodde and dronke dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth blacke coloure. Alſo it ſtereth a man moch to lechery, and he vſe it. Alſo it helpeth a man to make water. Alſo the ioyce of this herbe clenſeth a man yf he be anoynted ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. Alſo the ioyce of this herbe delyuereth men and chyldren from the cowghe, this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Eufragia.</head>
               <p>EVfragia is an herbe called Eufraſſe: this herbe hath lytell leues lyke to her colour but they be not ſomoch as he, &amp; he hath a why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te flower. ¶ The vertue is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is good to he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le ſore iyen, he groweth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> medowes &amp; hylles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:18"/>
               <head>¶ Ebulus.</head>
               <p>EBulus is an herbe called walworte, it hath leues ſomdele lyke Erderen and he hath a longe ſtalke and groweth in feldes.</p>
               <p>¶ The vertue is that he is good to dyſtroye the dropſy, and ſcabbes, or tetters. Alſo this herbe draweth wicked humours out of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Edera.</head>
               <p>EDera is an herbe called yue, this is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon it is called howſys, &amp; towrys, and hath leues lyke to an herbe called bryan, and it bereth fruyte as it were bayes. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue therof is yf it be ſod and layde on a botche it healeth it ſoone. Alſo yf thy heade ake take the ioyce of this herbe with oyle of roſes, and ſeth them togyther in wyne, and anoynt thy hede therwith, and thou ſhalt be hole. Alſo yf thou wyl kepe thy heade from akynge in the ſonne, take the leues of this herbe, and pune them ſmall, and then tempre them with cyſell and the oyle of Roſes, and then anoynte thy forheade therwith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Edera terreſtris.</head>
               <p>EDera terreſtris is an herbe called orpyn, or heyhoue, this hath leues lyke to Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynt, but they be not ſo moche, and hath in the croppe a red flower. ¶ The vertue is yf
<pb facs="tcp:191753:19"/> it be put in potage amonge fleſſhe, he wyll make the fleſſhe tendre and neſſhe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Eborus.</head>
               <p>EBorus is an herbe called longe wort, or Pelyder of ſpayne, this is lyke to Pede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lion, but the leues of this herbe be not ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſlytte without, and he hath a flower as it were a paſnepe. ¶ The vertue is that he wyl hele ſcabbes, the morfewe, and tetters. Alſo he heleth the emerawdes, yf it be layde to the place there it bledeth. Alſo he purgeth the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the fleume. Alſo he helpeth the from the tothache yf it be ſod with eyſell, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a quantyte in your mouth. Alſo this herbe purgeth well the ſtomacke and the wombe. Alſo the powder of this herbe medled with a lytel growell ſhall ſlee wormes. Alſo the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of this herbe medled with mylke ſhall ſlee fleeſe, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Elabrus.</head>
               <p>ELabrus is an herbe called Clouentonge, or Pedelyon, this herbe is moche lyke to longe worte, but not ſo flat as be the leues of this herbe, &amp; he hath ſomdele a brode flower, more than a peny, he hath a blacke rote and he is horryble in ſyght. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that yf the powder therof be medled with growel or with meele it wyl ſlee rattes
<pb facs="tcp:191753:19"/> and yf a beeſt pyſſe blode, gyue hym this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be and he is hole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Epatica.</head>
               <p>EPatica is an herbe called liuerwort, this herbe groweth in brymmes of waters, and in welles, and it wyll ioyne to ſtones, and he groweth moche in walles of ſtone, &amp; it hath nother ſtalke, not her flower but ſmall to wnde leues, and the more the leues be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to medycynes. ¶ The vertue is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll dyſtroy and clenſe the hardenes of the lyuer. Alſo the leues therof medeled with ſwynes grece wyll hele woundes. Alſo it is good to hele the Feuer quartayne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .vi. letter begynneth with .F.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Famula.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Amula is an herbe called ſperworte, or la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecle, this hath leues ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to a ſpere hed, it hath a ſtalke, and in the top co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng out many ſmal ſtalkes, &amp; it hath a why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te flower, and it groweth in waters. ¶ The vertue therof is that he is good to hele the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and alſo for to breke botches and byles, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:20"/>
               <head>¶ Fumus terre.</head>
               <p>FUmus terre is an herbe called fumeterry this herbe hath leues that ben ſomwhat whyte vnder, and they ben ſmal, and it hath a flower of purpul colour, and this herbe gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth in ſtalkes, but not fullonge. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue is that he comforteth the ſtomacke. Alſo he maketh a man to haue appetyde to mete, it helpeth a man to make water, and it openeth the ſtoppynge of the lyuer, &amp; clereth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes blode. Alſo yf the ioyce therof be dronke it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth ſcabbes and ytchynge, and bladders that ben gendred of wycked humours, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Fragra.</head>
               <p>FRagra is an herbe called ſtrawbery, and this herbe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon. ¶ The vertue therof is that he is good to dyſtroye a webbe in the lyen. Alſo it is good to hele woundes. Alſo the ioyce medeled with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and dronke he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the akynge of a mannes mylte, this gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in clene and darke places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Fabaria maior.</head>
               <p>FAbaria maior is an herbe called brokele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, this herbe hath rownde leues &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lyke to myntes. ¶ The vertue therof is, yf he be puned with ſhepes talowe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hote in maner of a playſter, and layde to
<pb facs="tcp:191753:20"/> any ſwellynge it wyll hele it, this herbe gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in ſmal brokes, &amp; moſte amonge belton.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Filex.</head>
               <p>FIlex is an herbe called Ferne, this herbe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, and there be .iii. ſpyces therof, one is called Ferne, and another is called po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipode, another called Oſmonde, and that is the .ii. ſpyces, another is called verrew &amp; that is the .iii. ſpyce, polipode is good to make a man laxatyue, and he groweth in trees, Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monde is good to hele broken bones, and it groweth in dyches and woodes, the .iii. that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal euer verrew groweth on walles, and is good to hele the potagre, &amp; he maketh ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſenewes, &amp; he groweth in woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, dyches, and feldes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Filipendula.</head>
               <p>FIlipendula is an herbe that men calleth Filipendull or dropworte, this is lyke to yaron, and he groweth next the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, the leues be more than the leues of yaron, it hath a ſmall ſtalke, and a flower ſomdele whyte, and in the more ſmall pelettes lyke yſhape as it were ſmal pelettes rownde. ¶ The vertue is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyll dyſtroy wycked wyndes aboute the lyuer and the mylte. Alſo he helpeth to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the ſtone, it groweth in holowe places, and drye, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:21"/>
               <head>¶ Feniculum.</head>
               <p>FEnicnlum is an herbe that men calleth Fenell, this herbe is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ynoughe.</p>
               <p>¶ The vertue is, the ſede when it is drye, it diſtroyeth wynde in the ſtomacke. Alſo it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth a mannes ſtomacke. Alſo he openeth the ſtoppynge of the reynes &amp; of the bladder. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of this herbe ſtilled in to a mans iye doth away the webbe. Alſo yf it be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with wyne, it dyſtroyeth all maner of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nym. Alſo the ioyce dropped in to the eres ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wormes, that ben within. Alſo yf it be dronke with wyne it heleth the dropſy. Alſo it heleth all maner of ſwellynges. Alſo yf he be dronke with wyne or water, it maketh a womans mylke to wax. Alſo yf he be dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with wyne, it kepeth from caſtyng. Alſo yf he be medled with oyle it wyll hele y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of a mans yerde. Alſo yf thou wyll be ſteryed to lecherye, take and drynke the ſede therof with good wyne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Faxmus.</head>
               <p>FAxmus is an herbe called hertwort or odobrame, this hath leues yſhape as a hert and hath a flower as were bugle, and a ſhorte ſtalke. ¶ The vertue is yf he be broke and layde to a ſore it heleth anone, this groweth in feldes and medowes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:21"/>
               <head>¶ Finiculus porcinus.</head>
               <p>FIniculus porcinus is an herbe called ſwynes fenel or worme ſede, this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be hath ſmall leues lyke to yaron, and of a ſtalke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge many braunches it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth vpon walles, &amp; hath ſmall coddes and ſmall red ſede. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is, yf a man ete the ſede therof, it diſtroyeth and ſleyeth the wormes within the wombe, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Febrifuga.</head>
               <p>FEbrifuga is called fetherfoy or vethut foye, this herbe hath many ſtalkes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge out of one ſtalke, and it hath a whyte flower as it were Mayes. ¶ The vertue is that he wyl comforte the ſtomacke. Alſo it ſwageth the feuer cotydyan. Alſo it is good to hele the crampe that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of a colde ſtomacke. Alſo yf this herbe be puned and layde to a ſore that is bytten with a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymous worme or beeſt it ſhall be hole. Alſo this herbe tempered with eyſell doth awaye the morfew. Alſo yf this be puned and layde to a wounde, in the whiche is broken bones, it ſhal hele the bones. Alſo the rote of this her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be is good to ſtaunche the blodymenſon, this is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Filago.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:22"/>
               <p>FIlago is an herbe called feldewort, this herbe hath leues a lytell enlong, and it is lyke to hore hounde, it is a lytell herbe and it groweth in wete.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mula minor.</head>
               <p>FLa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mula minor is an herbe called the leſſe ſperwort, it hath leues as it were graſſe, but it is ſharpe as it were a ſpere. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of this herbe is yf it be puned and layde to a hande that is byte, it ſhallbe hole anone.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .vii. letter begynneth with .G.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Granum.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ranum is an herbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gromell, or lytelwale, this hath leues that ben par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te enlonge, and hath a lytell whyte ſede ſhape as a ſtone that men call mariery perle. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he is good to hele the ſtone, and the euyl of the bledder, this herbe maketh a man to make water, and this is hote &amp; dry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Geneſcula.</head>
               <p>GEneſcula is an herbe called Geneſtre, or brome, this hath leues lyke to Spy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurnell, and they ben a lytell longer, and it hath a yelowe flower. ¶ The vertue is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is good to knyt bones &amp; ſynewes togyther.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:22"/>
               <head>¶ Genciana.</head>
               <p>GEnciana is an herbe called bladmoyne or felde wort. ¶ The vertue of this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be is that he clenſeth the ſtoppynge of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, the lyuer and the mylte, &amp; it be dronke with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and water. Alſo it healeth the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of venymous beeſtes. Alfs;o it delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a woman of a deade chylde, and this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Galanga.</head>
               <p>GAlanga is an herbe that men call Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngale. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he comforteth the ſtomacke, &amp; it maketh a man to defye his meate. Alſo it vnbyndeth and letteth out wycked wyndes out of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes body. Alſo it maketh a mannes mouthe ſwete. Alſo it healeth the reynes. Alſo it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a man to haue appetyte to a woman, &amp; it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Granum ſolis.</head>
               <p>GRanum ſolis is an herbe called wylde Gromell, this hath leues ſomdele lyke to Gromell, and his ſede is lyke ſomdele to that other gromell ſede. Alſo he hath ſomdele ſuche a flower, neuertheles they dyffereth in the ſtalke, for the ſtalke of this herbe is ſharp and it groweth moche in wete.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Gladiolus.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:23"/>
               <p>GLadiolus is an herbe called Gladyoll, or Gladur, this herbe hath leues like to an herbe called Getus, but it is not ſo grene, it hath a yelow flower &amp; a longe ſtalke, and it groweth in water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Graciadei.</head>
               <p>GRaciadei is an herbe called graciadei, this hath leues ſomdele lyke to dens de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lion, but the leues of this be ſomwhat ſharp, and it hath yelowe flowers, and it groweth in drye lande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Graciadei maior.</head>
               <p>GRaciadei maior is an herbe called gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciadei the more, this hath leues lyke to cokyll, &amp; it hath a whyte flower, it groweth in drye grounde, and whan that it is broke it droppeth mylke.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .viii. letter begynneth with .H.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Haſtula regia.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aſtula regia is an herbe called wodrofe, it hath leues lyke to croyes wort, and this herbe is ſote in ſauour, and a woman ſmel moche therto it maketh her heade to ake. ¶ The vertue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is yf the more of it be puned with wyne it ſhall hele ſores of the mouthe. Alſo take the
<pb facs="tcp:191753:23"/> ſede of this herbe and pune it and tempre it with the ſowreſt eyſel that ye can fynde and drynke it, and it ſhall ſtaunche the flyxe and harde the wombe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Herba crucita.</head>
               <p>HErba crucita is an herbe called Croys worte or Exean, this hath lytell leues and a ſmall ſtalke, and alſo a whyte flower. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll hele well woundes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Herba chriſtofori.</head>
               <p>HErba chriſtofori maſculus is an herbe called herbe chriſtofer male, this herbe hath leues moche lyke to leſſe croweſape, but they ben more whyte and not fully ſo longe, and it groweth in drye grounde, and alſo in watery places, and it hath a yelowe flower. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he is good to hele the peſtylence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Herba walteri.</head>
               <p>HErba walteri is an herbe called herbe water, this hath leues lyke to the leues of Perſely, and the leues be thycke, fat, and tender. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll clenſe woundes and hele them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Herba Roberti.</head>
               <p>HErba Roberti is an herbe called herbe Robert, this hath leues lyke to herbe
<pb facs="tcp:191753:24"/> Genet, it hath a ſmall flower that is ſomdel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, it groweth in feldes and in hedges, and in walles. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyll hele woundes, and alſo the powder wyll ſlee the Canker.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Herba martis.</head>
               <p>HErba martis is an herbe called morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, this herbe hath leues lyke to a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. M. when he is a capytall letter, &amp; in ſome brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che ht hath .ix. leues, and ſome more, and ſome fewer, and bringeth forth her leues and ſede togyther, this herbe hath many wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vertues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Herba Iohannis.</head>
               <p>HErba Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis is an herbe called ſaynt Iohanes worte, it hath leues lyke to the leſſe Centory, it hath a yelow flower and a longe ſtalke, and many ſtalkes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng of one. ¶ The vertue is yf he be in a howſe, he ſuffreth no wycked ſpryte dwell therin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Herba Petri.</head>
               <p>HErba Petri is an herbe called cowſlop this herbe hath leues lyke to herbe <abbr>xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o</abbr> for femall, but they be more whyter, and it groweth in medowes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .ix. letter begynneth with .I.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Iuſquiamus.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:24"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vſquianus is an herbe called Henbane or He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nebel, this herbe hath leues ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what whyte vnder, and the leues be flat a lytel without as it were ſowthiſtel, it hath a flower ſomwhat white, and it hath a great ſtalke, and many braunches co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge out of one more, &amp; it groweth in hye wayes. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that the oyle made ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of is good to dyſtroye all maner of gowtes, and namely that that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of melancolye. Alſo the ſede of this herbe layde on a ſlayte ſtone and hete with the fyre, and let it ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in the mans mouthe, it ſleeth wormes of the teth. Alſo he ſwageth the cough and hote poſtume and hote potegre. Alſo the more is good for the tothache, and the ioyce of this is good for all maner of woundes, and the ſede therof ſhulde be gathered in Auguſt. Alſo yf thou caſt the ſede therof in the fyre, all the he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that ben ouer the fyre ſhall fall in to the fyre, and it is colde and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Iſopus.</head>
               <p>ISopus is an herbe called Iſope, it hath leues lyke to Sauery, but they be not ſo brode, &amp; he flowreth as doth ſauery. ¶ The vertue therof is that the ioyce therof
<pb facs="tcp:191753:25"/> medled with eyſell, and put in a ſore mouth heleth it. Alſo it ſleeth wormes in the wombe and maketh the wombe neſſhe. Alſo yf it be dronke grene or els the powder, it maketh a man wel colowred, it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Ireoſe.</head>
               <p>IReoſe is an herbe called Saue, and his leues be lyke to flowerdelyce, &amp; it hath a whyte flower, and groweth in water.</p>
               <p>¶ The vertue therof is that he wyll hele the akynge of the ſenewes. Alſo it diſtroyeth the coughe. Alſo yf it be dronke with wyne it dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroyeth the wycked humoures of the breeſt. Alſo it helpeth the bytyng of venymous bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes or wormes. Alſo it diſtroyeth the crampe Alſo it delyuereth a woman of a deade chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Iris.</head>
               <p>IRis is an herbe called flowerdelyſe and it is lyke to Saue almoſte in all maner fetures, but this herbe hath a flower al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte of purpull colour, this groweth in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and gardaynes, and he hath the ſame ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tues that Saue hath.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Iua.</head>
               <p>IUa is an herbe called Iue, this herbe hath a rote euen downe to the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de growyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and it hath ſmall leues growyng euen by
<pb facs="tcp:191753:25"/> the grounde. ¶ The vertue is yf a man haue a ſore ſwellyng aboute his eres, take this her be cumbonfitatibus of her in wyne and oyle and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn, and than make a playſter therof, and laye to the eares and it ſhall hele theym. Alſo take the knobbes of the rote &amp; dry them and clenſe them, and they haue vertue to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte the laxatyue, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Iaſia alba.</head>
               <p>IAſia alba is an herbe called wylde Tan ſey or goſe graſſe, but they be more why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and it hath a yeſowe flower, and it groweth downe by the grownde, as doth the ſtrawberyes. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is good for the clenſyng of a mans lymmes, it groweth in medowes, ſees, wodes, &amp; wayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Iaſia nigra.</head>
               <p>IAſia nigra is an herbe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men call matfe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, or bulwede, or yrenhard, or knoppe wede, this hath leues lyke to ſcabyous, and it hath a purpull colour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Ippia maior.</head>
               <p>IPpia maior is an herbe called pympernel, or ſefehele, or wayworte, or more croppe, this hath leues lyke to chyckewede, but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues of this ben leſſe, and it hath a flower of purpull colour, &amp; it groweth in wete. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he is good to hele
<pb facs="tcp:191753:26"/> wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and ſo dyſtroy venym, and is good for the poſtume, and to hele the ſore iyen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Ipia minor.</head>
               <p>IPia minor is an herbe that men call cheke wede, this herbe hath leues like to pymper nell, and it hath a whyte flower, and it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in gardaynes and in feldes. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of this herbe is, ſethe it in ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge water and waſſhe your ſcabey handes therin often tymes, and they ſhall be hole.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .x. letter begynneth with .L.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Laniſticum.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Aniſticum is an her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be called louage, this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be hath leues lyke to Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage, but they be ſomde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le more, &amp; it hath a longe ſtalke, and it is ſtronge in ſauour. ¶ The vertue is in the ſede of her. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morys therof dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with wyne, is good for the ſtomacke, and for good dygeſtyng, this is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lingua ceruina.</head>
               <p>LIngua ceruina is an herbe called hertes tongue, this hath leues lyke to the tonge of a harte, and it groweth in walles and drye places, &amp; hath no ſede, nor flower, nor ſtalke.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:26"/>
               <p>¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he wyl ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poſtume and breke it, yf it be ſode with oyle of Roſes. Alſo yf it be dronke with olde wyne, it hardyneth the wombe. Alſo it hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a man of the coughe, this is hote &amp; drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lilium.</head>
               <p>LIlium is an herbe that men call Lylye. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that yf thou pune it with talowe, and ſethe it with oyle, and laye it to the place there as the colde poſtume is, it ſhall rype hym and breke hym. Alſo take the rotes of lylye, and the rotes of the red docke, and the more of louage, &amp; put all theſe in wyne &amp; oyle, the ſpace of .ii. dayes and afterward let it ſeth and clenſe it, and do therto waxe and oyle, and make anoyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and that is good to hele the ſores &amp; hardenes of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes mylte. Alſo take the knobbes of the rotes of the Lylye and roſt them amonge the coles, and take oyle Olyue and anoynte there as the ſore is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Liguſtrum.</head>
               <p>LIguſtrum is an herbe called prymeroſe. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is good for to make potage. Alſo the ioyce put in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes noſe wyll dyſtroy the Megrym. Alſo the water that the rote is ſoden in is good to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtop the conduytes of vryne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:27"/>
               <head>¶ Lingua bouis.</head>
               <p>LIngua bouis is an herbe called Langde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> befe. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is good to do awaye the red colour of a man. Alſo yf it be dronken it doth away the cardyacle and other wycked humours in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes lunges. Alſo the ioyce of this herbe dronke with hote water, maketh a man to haue a good mynde and good wyt, this muſt be gathered in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne or in Iuly, and this is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lingua ſerpentis maior.</head>
               <p>LIngua ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ris maior is an herbe called Adder tongue, this herbe hath leues ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to Affodyll, but they be more grene, and al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo more ſharp in the ende, this muſt be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the moneth of Apryll.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lingua ſerpentis minor.</head>
               <p>LIngua ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis minor is an herbe called the leſſe Adder tongue, this herbe hath leues ſomwhat lyke to Pygyll, and it hath a yelowe flower, and out of the ſtalke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth many brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches, and it groweth in woodes.</p>
               <p>¶ The vertue of this herbe is good to lay to a cut, yf it be bruſed and layde therto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lingua canis.</head>
               <p>LIngua canis is an herbe called houndes tongue. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is good to dyſtroy the coughe and the poſtume,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:27"/> and it wyll rype a botche. Alſo this herbe ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten is good for ſhakynge of the heed, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth the throte and the breth ſmothe &amp; ſouple. Alſo for the flux of the wombe yf thy fete be waſſhed in the water that it is ſoden in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lingua hircina.</head>
               <p>LIngua hircina is an herbe called Bucke ſhorne, or ſwyneſkerce, this herbe hath le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues flatred as it were an hertes horne, and it groweth crepynge by the grownde, &amp; it hath a lytell whyte flower, it groweth in watery places. ¶ The vertue is that is clenſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke and refreyneth the great hete, and hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth the brennynge of fyre, yf that it be ſoden and layde therto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lupinus.</head>
               <p>LUpinus is an herbe called Lupyne, this herbe hath leues lyke to fyue leued gras, the Lupyne hath .vi. leues, and it hath a why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te flower, and a whyte ſede that is ſomwhat broder, and it bereth coddes ſomwhat lyke to benecoddes. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is, yf a man haue wormes in his wombe, take the ſede and make meele therof, and the ioyce of worm wode and ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and make a cake ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of and ete it, and it vnbyndeth the ſtoppynge of the lyuer &amp; of the mylte. Alſo it is good to dyſtroy the dropſy. Alſo take the ſame meele
<pb facs="tcp:191753:28"/> and the ioyce of arſmert, &amp; make therof paſte and lay it to thy eres, and it ſhal kyl the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes within them or yf thou make a cake ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of &amp; hete it, it wyll do the ſame. Alſo yf thou wyll take the ioyce of Lekes, and tempre it with the meele, and put it in thy eres, it ſhall clenſe theym from all wycked humours and ſtynkyng. Alſo take the ſame meele and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre it with oyle, and it wyl breke and rype all maner of poſtumes. And this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Labrum veneris.</head>
               <p>LAbrum veneris is an herbe that men cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth Sowthyſtell. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is this, yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue a hote feuer, take the ioyce therof and tempre it with hote wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let hym drynke it and he ſhall be hole. Alſo yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue venym within hym, take this herbe and drye it and make powder ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, and do the powder in good wyne, and let hym drynke it, and it wyll caſt vp all the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nym, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lauendula.</head>
               <p>LAuendula is an herbe called lauander, yf this be ſoden in water, and gyuen to a man that hath the palſye, it wyll hele hym, and this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lactuca.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:28"/>
               <p>LActuca is a herbe that is called Lettyſe or ſlope worte. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is this, yf it be eten rawe or ſoden it engendreth good blode. Alſo this herbe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with a lytel eyſel and Saffron and than dronken, it helpeth a man that is ſtopped in the lyuer and in the mylt. Alſo yf a man may not ſlepe, take the ſede of this herbe &amp; ſtampe it to powder, &amp; tempre it with womans myl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and make a playſter therof on lynt, &amp; lay it to the temples of thy heade, &amp; thou ſhalt ſlepe well, or elles drynke the powder therof with mylke. Alſo take the ſede and tempre it with oyle of roſes, and make a playſter and lay it to thy ſtomacke, and it is good to diſtroy the hote poſtume. Alſo drynke the ioyce of this herbe, or powder the ſede for it is good to he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flyx, but who that vſeth this herbe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moche, it wyll dyſtroy theyr ſyght, this herbe is colde and ſomwhat moyſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lactuca ſiluatica.</head>
               <p>LActuca ſiluatica is an herbe called wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Lettyſe, this herbe hath leues lyke to the thiſtel, and they be ſharpe and kene, and it hath a flower of purpull colour, and it groweth in feldes and in whete, this herbe is hote and drye. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that it taketh away the dymnes of the iyes,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:29"/> medle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of this herbe with wyne or ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and the gall of an Auſtour, or other foule of pray, and put it all medled in a glaſſe, and put it in thy iyes .iii. tymes in a day or more, and in ſhorte ſpace thy iyes ſhallbe clere, for it is a ſouerayne medicyne. And bycauſe this herbe is good for to clere the ſyght, ſome ſay that the Egle cateth this herbe when that he wyll flee hye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lactuca leporica.</head>
               <p>LActuca leporica is an herbe called Hate thyſtel, this herbe hath leues lyke vnto Sowthyſtel, but the leues be not ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented, it droppeth mylke. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is thus yf a hare cate of this herbe in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer whan he is mad, he ſhallbe hole.</p>
               <p>Alſo take this herbe &amp; lay it to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſyde when he ſlepeth, or elles that he knowe not therof, and it wyll hele hym of the feuers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Lollium.</head>
               <p>LOllium is an herbe that men call cokle. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is thus, yf it be dronken with Radyſſhe, and a lytel ſalt, it is good to hele the Canker, or other wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des in peryll. Alſo it is good to comforte the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuer. Alſo it wyll vnbynde the wormes in a mans ſtomacke. Alſo it helpeth a man to make water, and it is good for ſore
<pb facs="tcp:191753:29"/> iyes. Alſo ſubfumygacyon therof wyl make a woman to bere her chylde without any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryll or harme. Alſo it wyll aſſwage the great paynes of akynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lypur, it is hote &amp; dry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Laparium rubeum.</head>
               <p>LAparium rubeum is an herbe called red docke, yf that a man take the ioyce ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of and holde it in his mouth, it wyll aſſwage the tothache. Alſo yf a man haue the kynges euyl take this herbe and ſeth it in wyne, and ſtrayne it and gyue it hym to drynke, and he ſhallbe hole yf he vſe it oft. Alſo yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man rubbe hym with the ioyce, it doth away euyll ytchynges. Alſo this herbe is good to deliuer wyndes that be ſtopped in a mans ſtomacke by balkyng. Alſo this herbe is good to make ſcabbes and botches rype. Alſo it is good to make a man to haue a harde wombe, &amp; this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Linum.</head>
               <p>LInum is an herbe that men cal flex, and it is good yf a man take the ſede therof, and ſethe it in water, it maketh a man laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyue, and it is good to make a playſter therof for akynge ſores. Alſo there is another ſpyce therof that is called Cuſtula, and it is named in englyſſhe Dodure, &amp; it groweth amonge flex. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he is
<pb facs="tcp:191753:30"/> good to purge a man of the colour. Alſo yf a great quantyte therof be taken, and ſoden in Myrre and oyle togyther, and a playſter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de therof, it is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raynes and for the breeſt, and for other akynge lymbes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>Lauriola.</head>
               <p>LAuriola is a herbe called lawrell. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that it wyll make a man laxatyue, &amp; it is good to purge a man of flewme and of colour, it is good for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that may not cate, for yf the ioyce therof be put in his eres, or yf the ſayde herbe be ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, &amp; a ſuppoſitory be made therof and ſayde on cotton, it wyll hele it. Alſo for them that here not wel, put the ioyce in to his eres, and yf there be any rotten humours it wyll drye them, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Licoriſa.</head>
               <p>LIcoriſa is an herbe that men cal lycoryſe the rote of this herbe is ſwete, &amp; it moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the kyndly hete of a man, and it is good for the coughe. Alſo yf it be ſoden in water, it wyll dyſtroy a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes thurſte. Alſo it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes breſt, his throte, and his lunges moyſte, and in good tempre. Alſo the water that lycoryſe is ſoden in is good agaynſt all ſyckenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breeſt, &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> a poſtume of the rybbes called pleureſy, it is colde &amp; moyſte.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:191753:30"/>
            <head>¶ The .xi. letter begynneth with .M.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Millefolio minor.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Illefolio minor is an her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be that is called the leſſe Myl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foyle, there is no dyfference of kynde nor vertue betwene myl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>foyle the leſſe, and Mylfoyle the more, ſaue the more groweth in gardaynes, and the leſſe in wylde places, they be both of one ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth.</p>
               <p>¶ The vertue of this herbe ſhallbe declared in Mylfoyle the more folowynge by lettre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Mercurialis.</head>
               <p>MErcurialis is an herbe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men cal Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curye. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that he is good yf a man haue akynge in his wombe, gyue hym to drynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce and he ſhallbe hole, it wyll clenſe the ſtomacke, and the ſede wyll do the ſame. Alſo the ioyce tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pred with whyte wyne is good to hele ſore iyes, and yf a worme or other vermyn haue bytten a man, take the ioyce &amp; warme it, and waſſhe it. Alſo yf there be any wormes crope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in to a mans eres, take the ioyce and warme it and put it in to his eares, &amp; he ſhallbe hole, this is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Menta.</head>
               <p>MEnta is an herbe that men cal mynte. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that yf
<pb facs="tcp:191753:31"/> it be ofte eaten, it wyll ſlee the wormes in a mans wombe. Alſo yf a man haue botches or other rennynges or ſwellynges in his heade, take this herbe and ſtamp it, and lay it to the ſore, and it wyll hele it. Alſo yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes toth or the fleſſhe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> toth ake or ſtynke: take this herbe and ſeth it in whyte wyne and in eyſel, and take that lycour and waſſhe his mouthe therwith, than take the powder of the herbe and rubbe well his teth therwith, and he ſhal haue a ſwete ſmellynge mouthe. Alſo take thou this herbe and eyſell &amp; make ſauce, and it wyl make the to haue a talent to thy mete. Alſo when there ſhal be gyuen any medicyne to diſtroy venym, it wylbe good to be gyuen with the ioyce of this herbe, for it hath many vertues, and namely for venym, there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpyces therof, and it is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Menta romana.</head>
               <p>MEnta romana is an herbe that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> call whyte mynte. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is that the ioyce therof wyl ſle wormes in a mannes wombe. Alſo the ioyce wyll ſle wormes in the noſe thyrſſes of a man. Alſo the powder therof caſte in a mans mete, ſhall make hym well to defye his meate. Alſo the ioyce dronke ſleeth the wormes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wombe, yf it be dropped in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eres, it ſleeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wormes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:31"/>
               <head>¶ Malua.</head>
               <p>MAlua is an herbe that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal malowe. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is good yf the leues be ſtamped and layde to a mans ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, it wyll breke a hote poſtume in the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ynge, or els medle this herbe with freſſhe ſwynes grece, and laye it on a hote tyle, &amp; lay it all hote to the poſtume, and it ſhal rype it, and breke it. Alſo it is good to diſtroy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hard<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of a mans lyuer and mylte. Alſo it wyll make a man laxatyue, &amp; it is good for play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, it is colde and moyſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Morell or nyghtſhadowe.</head>
               <p>MOrell is an herbe that men call nyght ſhadowe, this herbe is colde and drye in the .ii. degre, the leues, the braunches, and the fruytes therof be ryght good &amp; beſt when they be grene. ¶ The vertue is they be good for ſtoppynge of the ſplen and the lyuer, and beſt for the Iaundeſſe to drynke the ioyce of it with a lytell Ruberbe. Alſo it is good for a poſtume in the ſtomacke, in the bowels, or in the lyuer, ſeth the ioyce therof with barly wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and drynke it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Maſtyke.</head>
               <p>MAſtyke is an herbe that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, and it is hote and drye in the .ii. degre, and it is a gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of a tre growynge in a parte
<pb facs="tcp:191753:32"/> of the countre of Grece, in the latter ende of Vcre the men of that countre ſlytte the trees, and than make the grownde clene all abouts and laye clothes rounde aboute the trees, or ſome other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me from the grounde in choſynge of it, to knowe whiche is beſt, to take the beſt is whyte and clere, the whyte colour is next y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is medled with carth and ſomwhat darke, the beſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyke hath vertue of conſtraynynge, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, clenſyng, and loſynge of humours diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cendyng from the hede aboue to the iyes and to the teth, and for the dyſeaſe of the tempſes made of an aſcendynge wynde from the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke to the heed. Take powder of maſtyke with whyte ſwete wyne, and the whyte of an egge, and medle them well togyther, and ye wyll ye may put in frankenſence, &amp; play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it to the temples. Alſo ſethe Maſtyke in water and drynke it, and it wyl comfort wel the ſtomacke and make good degeſtyon, and it comforteth and relaxeth the ſtomacke, and put to it feneſ ſede, and it putteth out wynde out of the ſtomacke. Alſo a playſter made of Maſtyke and bole armonyake, and the why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of an egge and vynegre, and laye it on the forke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomacke or breſt, it wyll conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne wel the coloryke vanyte. Alſo ſeth maſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
<pb facs="tcp:191753:32"/> in rayne water and drynke it warme, and this medycyne is very good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flux of the wombe that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of a ſharp lax that was taken before to ſtop hym. Alſo boyle maſtyke in rayne water, or Roſe water, with two or thre cloues, and drynke it warme, &amp; that com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forteth the vomyte, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flux of the wombe that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of ſharpnes and vyolence of the medycyne. Alſo maſtyke muſt haue but lytell boylynge for hurtynge of his vertue, and it ſhulde be gyuen warme, for it conſtrayneth the more whan that it is gyuen warme, than whan it is ouer moche hote.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Magerum.</head>
               <p>MAgerum is an herbe that is hote &amp; dry in the ſeconde degre, the flowers and leues be vſed in medycynes, and it ſhulde be gathered in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer whan it flowreth, and dry it in the ſhadowe, and it may be kepte a yere. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is good in comfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge, loſynge, conſumynge, and of clenſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, yf the powder of it be dronken in wyne, or els boyle the powder of it in wyne, and it wyll hete wel a ſtomacke. Alſo it comforteth the degeſtyon. Alſo take the leues &amp; flowers of magerum, and pune them a lytell, &amp; make them hote in a pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, and lay it to the greuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and it taketh awaye the dyſeaſe in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke
<pb facs="tcp:191753:33"/> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of wynde. Alſo for the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me in the heade, take this herbe and bynde it warme aboute thy heade. Alſo it dryeth the mother and conſumeth the ſuperfluyte of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Millefolium maior.</head>
               <p>MIllefolium maior or yarow is an her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kynge Achylles dyd fynde, and therwith heled his men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded with yron. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is good for woundes, ſtampe this herbe with ſwynes grece, and playſter it to the wounde, and it ſhal hele it, and the ſame is good for an ache in the breſte or ſyde, it is good for hym that may not pyſſe, take the ioyce of this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be and vinegre &amp; drynke it, and merueylouſly it helpeth a wounde that hath taken colde, ſtampe this herbe in butter, and laye it to the wounde, and it wyll hele it well. Alſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomacke or that lyeth therin, take the ioyce of it, &amp; medle it with water and ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nye, and drynke it warme. Alſo it is good for dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes in the body, take the powder and medle it with wyne or with good ale, and drynke it and it helpeth moche. Alſo it is good for the herte brennynge. Alſo for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heedache ſtampe this herbe, and playſter it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heade. Alſo for bytynge of a wood dogge, ſtampe this herbe with the graynes of wete, and it healeth it.
<pb facs="tcp:191753:33"/> Alſo for hym that may not holde his meate, take and ſtampe this herbe with wyne, and drynke it warme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Motherworte.</head>
               <p>MOtherworte or mogwort, this herbe is called in latyn Artemeſia, and it is hote and drye in the thyrde degre, this herbe helpeth a woman to conceyue a chylde, clenſeth the mother, and maketh a woman to haue her flowers, and it dyſtroyeth the eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rawdes on this maner. Fyrſte it muſt be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, than take the powder of motherwort, and of Horehounde togyther, and ſtrawe it on the pappes. Alſo yf a chylde be deed in the mothers wombe, take motherwort, &amp; ſtampe it ſmall, and make a playſter therof and lay it to her wombe all colde, and with the grace of God ſhe ſhall haue delyuetaunce without parell, it is good for the ſtone and the grauell in the raynes of a man or of a woman, yf a man bere this herbe vpon hym, there ſhall no venymous beeſt greue hym. It is good for the yelowe Iaundes and it be dronken with wyne, for it conforteth the ſtomacke, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth a man or woman to haue a good colour. Agaynſt ache of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bowels, powdre of mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort dronken with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny eaſeth greatly, and is good agaynſt many other ſyckeneſſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:34"/>
               <head>¶ Maces.</head>
               <p>MAces is a ſpyce that is called Mace, this ſpyce is hote &amp; drye in the ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de degre, maces is the tynde or huſke that groweth aboute the Nutmege, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de groweth aboute the haſell nutte, it may be kepte .x, yere in his vertue, it is comfortyng, dyſſoſuyng, and conſumyng, the knowledge of fyne maces is thus, it ſhulde be in coloure lyke to fyne golde, or elles lyke to golde that ſyluer is gyft with, the whiche hath a ſharpe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alage with a bytternes, and it ſoketh lyke to earth, &amp; it is to be refuſed, for it hath no ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe ſauour, for a colde ſtomacke that may not defye nor degeſte well, take maces and boyle them in wyne &amp; drynke it. Alſo a good play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the whiche is beſt for a feble ſtomacke, and make powdre of maſtyke and of maces, and medle them with oyle of Roſes &amp; wexe, and make a playſter therof and ſay it on the ſtomacke of the ſycke parſon. Alſo to clenſe the brayne of ſuperfluous humoures, take a quantyte of maces, and chewe them well in thy mouthe, &amp; holde them there a whyle, and that ſhall loſe the feumoſyte of humours that ryſe vp to the brayne, &amp; purge the ſuperfluite of it. Alſo for febleneſſe of the ſtomacke and the lyuer of a colde cauſe, and for the colyke,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:34"/> and for the dyſeaſes of the ſpyrytuall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, or flewme, boyle maces in the ioyce of fenell, and in the ende of the boyfynge put in a lytell wyne, than ſtrayne it and drynke it, for it is the beſt remedye for the foreſayd dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes. Alſo for the ache of the hert, vſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre of maces in thy meates and drynkes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Menta.</head>
               <p>MEnta is an herbe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is called red mynt, it is hote and dry in the ſeconde degre, and there be two other myntes, but I meane howſe myntes, the whiche properly is ſayde gardayne myntes, for that moſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly is in medycynes both grene and drye, for great holſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes it ſhuld be dried in a ſhadowe place, and ſo it wyll be kept a yere in great vertue, to dyſſolue or loſe, to conſume, of his proper qualyte, &amp; to comforte of his ſwete ſauoure. ¶ The vertue is this, for the ſtynkyng of the mouth and fylthe of the gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes &amp; of the teth, waſſhe thy mouth and gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes with vynegre that myntes be ſodden in, and after rub hym with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> powder of myntes, or with dry myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to prouoke the appetyte when a impedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomacke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of colde humours beyng in the mouth of the ſtomacke, make a ſalue of myntes and vynegre with a lytel ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namum and peper, and vſe it wel agaynſt vo
<pb facs="tcp:191753:35"/> mytes that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of feblenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomacke or of colde cauſes, ſethe myntes in ſauge wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and vynegre, and depe it in and laye it on the mouthe of the ſtomacke with the myntes that be ſoden therin. Alſo gyue to the pacient to eate of the ſame myntes for the ſincopyne, and febleneſſe in feuers, and without feuers, or of medycyne, or of what cauſe it be, ſtamp myntes with vynegre, and a lytell wyne yf the pacyent be without feuer, &amp; yf he be with feuer, ſtampe myntes with vynegre alone, than make a toſte of ſowre brede, and toſte it well tyl it be almoſte brent, then put it in that licour, and let it lye therin tyl it be wel ſoked, than put it in to his noſe and rub his lyppes, and gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, tethe, and temples therwith, and bynde it to the poulſe vaynes of his armes, &amp; let the pacyent eate the moyſtnes that is left and ſwalowe it in. For to clenſe the mother, take the tender croppes of myntes, and ſethe them in water or wyne, and playſter it to the ſhare, and to the raynes. Agaynſt the congy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge in a womans breſte, take the ſmall ſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of myntes and ſeth them in wyne &amp; oyle, and playſter it aboute the teates. Alſo be it knowen that whan any medycyne ſhulde be gyuen agaynſt venym, it ſhuld be gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ioyce of myntes, for myntes haue a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:191753:35"/> of ſtrengthe of drawynge out venym, or els it ſhuld be gyuen with wyne that myntes haue be ſoden in. For ſtoppynge of the ſplen and the lyuer, and of the wayes of the vryne of a colde humour and a hote without feuer, take the ioyce of myntes alone, or myntes ſo den in wyne, or the ioyce of myntes medled with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, &amp; gyue it to the pacyent. To ſlee wormes in the bely, take the ioyce of myntes and drynke it, &amp; thou ſhalte be hole. Alſo the ioyce of myntes ſleeth wormes in the eares. For a tetter take the ioyce of myntes, and put therto brymſtone and vynegre, &amp; medle them wel togyther, and anoynt the tetter therwith and thou ſhalte be hole. For a wounde in the heade, ſtamp myntes &amp; lay on the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. &amp;c. For payne in the ſyde, take myntes and ſeth them in olde wyne or ale, and with it ſtamp. xviii. graynes of peper, and drynke it in the nyght, and it wyll eaſe the of thy payne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .xii. letter begynneth with .N.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Nux muſcata.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Vx muſcata is a herbe the whiche is called a nutmeg, it is hote and drye in the ſeconde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre, the beſt groweth in ynde, &amp; in the tyme of his rypynge it is gathered, and
<pb facs="tcp:191753:36"/> ſeuen yere it may be kept, they that be playne and heuy after theyr kynde, be beſt to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. And when they be broken they fal not to powder, but they haue a ſwete and ſharpe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, yf they lacke any of theſe aforeſayde, they be not good for medycyne. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is of comfortynge by his ſwete ſauoure. For coldnes and feblenes of degeſtion of the ſtomacke, take in the mornynge halfe a nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg or a hole nutmeg, and eate it. Alſo for a colde ſtomacke that is feble of degeſtion, and for the lyuer, gyue hym wyne that nutmegꝭ is boyled in. Alſo for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame boyle nutmegꝭ and maſtyke in wyne and drynke it, this is good for the dyſeaſes in the ſtomacke, and in the bowels to breke wynde. Alſo in the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerynge of a ſyckenes to comforte the ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall membres, boyle nutmegꝭ and maſtyke in wyne, and drynke it. Alſo take a nutmeg and ſmell to it, and it wyl comforte the ſpyry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall membres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Napo.</head>
               <p>NApo this is named Nauew, it deſyreth grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that is fatty, and ſandy, it gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth beſt in ſuch grounde, the properte of the Nauewe is, he chaungeth and tourneth in to rape, and after that it tourneth in to nauew, the beſt doth growe in grounde well dunged
<pb facs="tcp:191753:36"/> and tourned. Alſo it proueth well in places that ſtubble of corne hath ben in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame yere, yf they growe to thycke, plucke ſome vp here and there, ſo that the other may proue the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, and thoſe that ye plucke vp, ſet them in voyde places. They ſhuld be ſowen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of Iuly, &amp; in Auguſt, the beſt ſauoured Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uewes be they that be longe &amp; ſtrayghte, and not ouer great, nor brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches in the rotes, but a ſtrayghte rote. Alſo of Nauewes maye be made a paſſynge good mete with a lytel ſalt and vynegre, honny and muſtarde, and with ſwete ſpyces, and it maye be made without ſpices, Nauewes be hote in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de degre, and they noryſſhe moche, but they be harde of degeſtyon, they make the fleſſhe ſofte &amp; wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but leſſe wynde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rapes. Therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſeth them in water, caſt that water away, and ſethe theym in another water, and ſo his harde ſubſtaunce is tempred by that, and ſo menely bytwene good and euyll they gendre noryſſhyng, for they that be thus well ſoden be not harde of degeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they make one wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and they make ſtoppynge of vaynes and of poores, but yet they be profytable yf they be ſoden twyſe, &amp; both the waters to be caſte away, and they to be ſoden in the thyrde wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with fatte fleſſhe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:191753:37"/>
            <head>¶ The .xiii. letter begynneth with .O.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Olibanum.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Libanum is called Frankenſence, this is hote and dry in the thyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de degre, it is a gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of a tre in ynde, the cleneſt is the beſt. Alſo there be trees of that kynde gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng in Damaſke, but not ſo clere nor good for it is darker of coloure, therfore it is to be refuſed in medycyne. ¶ The vertue is of com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fortynge by his ſwete ſauour. Alſo of cloſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and conſtraynynge, for the tothache that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of ſuperfluyte of humours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heed, and ſpecyally by the vaynes, make a playſter of the powder of Frankenſence with wyne, and the whyte of an egge, and medle them to gyther, and playſter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> them aboute the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples. Alſo to ſtop the wayes of the vaynes aboue, take Frankenſence, and chewe it well in thy mouth, and that ſhal ſtop and let the fluxe of humours co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge downe to the noſthyrles, take pylles of Frankenſence, and ſwalowe them downe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mornynge, than boyle fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenſence in wyne, and at euen drynke that whan thou goeſt to bed. Alſo theſe pylles be good to helpe the degeſtyon of the ſtomacke,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:37"/> and good agaynſt ſore balkyngꝭ. Alſo to the comfortynge and clenſynge of the matryce, and helpynge of concepcyon in the receyuyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the fume of Frankenſence byndeth. Alſo boyle powder of it in wyne, and whan it is metely warme dyp a cloth in it, and laye it ſo warme to the ſhare of the pacyent, and great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly it comforteth the matryce.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .xiiii. lettre begynneth with .P.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Plumeus.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes be colde &amp; moyſt ſome be whyte, and ſome be blacke, &amp; ſome be red. They that be blacke and ſomwhat harde be the beſt, they be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Damſons, &amp; wlan they be rype gather them, and ſlyt them, &amp; ſprynge vynegre vpon them, and ſo they may be kept in a veſſel of woode a yeare, and fyrſte whan they be cut they muſt be layde in the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne .xv. dayes to drye. ¶ The vertue of theſe Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons haue coldnes &amp; clenſyng of the inwarde partes, wherfore they be good in feuers that be ſharpe, and for coſtyfnes of bely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of drynes, or of coloryke humours dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge, yf it be newe gyue it hym to eate, yf it be drye boyle it in water, and gyue it the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyent
<pb facs="tcp:191753:38"/> to drynke therof, this is good for the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer tercian, for ſtoppyng of the lyuer, for the Iau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and ſharp feuers, it ſofteth the bely, it is good for defaute of appetyte, and alſo for many other dyſeaſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Piper.</head>
               <p>PIper this is called Peper, it is hote and drye in the fourthe degre. There be thre maner of Pepers, blacke, whyte, and longe Peper. Diaſcorides and Conſtantyne ſaye, that they be fruytes of trees growyng in yn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and ſome ſaye that Peper is made blacke with brennyng in the fyre, for whan it is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered there be great multytude of ſerpentes aboute it, and therfore they put it in the fyre to brenne the ſerpentes that be a boute it, the Saraſyns dry it in an ouen, bycauſe it ſhall not encreaſe in an other lande, but of all the Pepers the blacke is beſt, and the moſte hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. ¶ The vertue is, take Peper and put it in to thy noſe thyrlles, and it wyll make the to neſe, and ſeth Peper and fygges in wyne, and drynke it, &amp; it wyll clenſe the ſpyrytuall membres of toughe humours, and it is good for the poſe that is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of colde. Alſo for the ſame cate powder of Peper with Fygges. Alſo powder of Peper put in a mans meate comforteth the degeſtion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomacke. Alſo
<pb facs="tcp:191753:38"/> put longe Peper in a roſted apple, and ete it, and it ſhall comforte the degeſtyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre of Peper wyll frete away deed fleſſhe or prowde fleſſhe, and longe Peper comforteth more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blacke. Alſo blacke Peper hath ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of loſyng, comfortynge, and of drawyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, it clenſeth the ſpyrytual membres of colde flewme, and vycyous humours, &amp; beſt when the powder of it is eaten with fygges, for he hath great ſtrength of hetyng &amp; comfortyng the ſtomacke, prouokynge appetyte, but to ſanguyne &amp; coloryke perſones it is not good to vſe Peper, for it dryeth and bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth blode, and it engendreth lepre, and other euyl ſycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Pluto ſayeth, that Peper is fowle to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inſyght without blacke, and within whyte, a ſharpe ſauoure and a ſwete odour, lytell in quantyte, and moche in vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Pympernell.</head>
               <p>PYmpernell is an herbe that groweth in ſandy places at the foote of the hylles.</p>
               <p>¶ The vertue is he is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyſtula and canker, &amp; he be puned and layde theron. Alſo it is good for dymnes of iyen, yf that they be waſſhed with the water that it is ſodden in. Alſo the ioyce of this herbe dronken wyl put away all venym from the body. Alſo this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be is good to hele woundes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:39"/>
               <head>¶ Pulegium.</head>
               <p>PUlegium is a herbe called Pulyol royall it is hote and drye in the thyrde degre, in the tyme of flowerynge it ſhuld be gathered, and it may be kept in his vertue a yere, when it ſhall be vſed in medycynes, take the leues with the flowers and ſtrype them fro the ſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. ¶ The vertue is of loſynge and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge. For a colde humour in the heed, take powder of it and hete it well in a ſkyllet, and all hote bynde it to the greuaunce without any lycoure. Alſo for a great colde taken in the heed, and for a toughe humour or a wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry humour, make a gargaryſme, ſeth Pulyol royall, and dry fygges in tarte vynegre, and take a good ſponful therof as hote as ye may ſuſtre it, and holde it in thy mouth tyl it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte colde, than put it out &amp; take as moche more, and do ſo thre or foure tymes, and that ſhal ſpurge thy heed wel of flew me Alſo ſeth it in wyne and drynke it, and it is good for the dyſeaſes in the ſtomacke in guttes, &amp; for colde cauſes, or for wynde in the ſtomacke. Alſo it is good for toughe flewme in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breſt, yf thou take powdre of it, and medle it with claryfyde ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and make a lectuary therof, and vſe to ete therof, or take the herbe therof and boyle it with wyne, ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, or water, and
<pb facs="tcp:191753:39"/> vſe to drynke therof. Alſo for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blacke colour drynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of it, but boyle it with wyne, and thou ſhalte be hole. Alſo for a ytchynge byle, lay this herbe in water, &amp; vſe to waſſhe the ytchyng therin warme, and thou ſhalt be hole. Alſo for ache take this herbe all grene, and ſtampe it and playſter it to the ache, and it wyll eaſe it. Alſo agaynſt the coughe boyle this herbe in wyne, &amp; drynke it luke warme, and this wyll make one pyſſe well. For the dyſeaſe in the bely, ſtampe this herbe with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myn and water, and lay it hote to the nauel, and lyghtly it ſhallbe hole. For the diſeaſe in the lyuer, ſtampe this herbe &amp; tempre it with water and vynegre, &amp; drynke the ioyce therof and thou ſhalt be hole. For an ache in the leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or armes, take the leues of elder and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyall royal of eueryche alyke moche, &amp; ſtamp them togyther wel, and playſter it to the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce, and it is good for the feuer tercyan, yf thou take the braunches of this herbe, and wrappe it in a good locke of woll, and gyue it to the pacyent, and lethym ſmell therto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fyuer come on hym, and that ſhal do hym great eaſe. For the heedache, take this herbe and bynde it faſt rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de about thy heed, and anone it ſeaſeth the ache. Alſo yf a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man haue a deed chylde in her wombe, ſtamp
<pb facs="tcp:191753:40"/> this herbe, &amp; gyue it her to drynke with olde wyne, and ſhe ſhallbe delyuered of it by the grace of god. For the crampe drynke the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce with vynegre faſtynge, and it wyll put it awaye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Pencedanum vel Feniculus Porcinus.</head>
               <p>PEncedanum, this herbe is called mayth hogges fenell, or mayden wede, this her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be is hote and drye in the thyrde degre, when this herbe is gathered for medicynes, the rote is better then the herbe, when the rotes be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered they maye be kepte all a yeare. ¶ The vertue is he purgeth, it is good for the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulyon or the flyxe, and good for ſtoppynge of the ſplen and the lyuer, Boyle this herbe in wyne or water, and gyue it to the pacyent to drynke. Alſo ſeth it in oyle &amp; wyne, and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it to the ſhare, and it wyll helpe the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulion or the flyxe. Alſo the ſame playſter is good for hardenes of the ſplen, it molyfyeth that. Alſo agaynſt the colde humours of the ſpyrytuall membres, gyue hym to drynke wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter with barly, and this herbe ſoden togyther, and yf it be a feruent colde humour, then ſeth the barly and the herbe in wyne, and gyue it to the pacyent to drynke with lycoryce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Petrocilium.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:40"/>
               <p>PEtrocilium, this is called perſley, this is hote &amp; moyſt in the thyrde degre. ¶ The vertue is it multyplyeth greatly mans blode and doth away the tyſyke. It helpeth wel to dyſtroy the Feuer tertian. It is good for the ſyde and the dropſye. It comforteth the herte and the ſtomacke. And it is good in potage, and to ſtoppe chekyns.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Peritorium.</head>
               <p>PEritorium, this herbe is called Peritory, and it is hote and drye. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is thus, yf a man haue an euyl ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke or elles akynge within hym, take this herbe and ſeth it in thy potage, and ete therof and thou ſhal do wel. Alſo this herbe is good to hele one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone, yf he be bathed with it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Plaſtinaca.</head>
               <p>PLaſtinaca, this is called a Paſnep, it is hote &amp; moyſte in the ſeconde degre, there be two maner of Paſneppes, the one is the Paſnep of the gardayne, and the other is the wylde Paſneppe, they be more vſed to meate than to medycyne. ¶ The vertue is to gendre thycke blode &amp; moche, wherfore it ſtyrreth the luſt of the body yf it be moche vſed, therfore it is good for a man that is newly recouered out of his great ſyckenes to vſe to eate of it a whyle. Alſo they be good to be eten rawe, or
<pb facs="tcp:191753:41"/> ſoden for the melancoly humours grene and not drye. To make a ſyrope to ſtyrre the luſte of the bodye, &amp; for to comforte the degeſtion, take rotes of Pas;neppes, and ſeth them well in water, than take them out and caſte away the water, and the rotes that be in gobettes boyle them agayne in water, than put therto ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny well claryfyed, and let them boyle vnto the thyckenes of ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynually ſtyrre it that it cleue not to the veſſell and in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the boylynge, put in Almondes yf ye haue theym, and in the ende of the boylynge put in Gynger, Galyngale, and a lytel Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Nutmeg, and other ſwete ſauoured ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Alſo Paſneppes maye be ſowen in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cembre, Ianuary, and Marche, in fat grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and depe doluen, and loſe grounde, and beſt dygged, and they be ſomwhat wyndy, boyle them in two waters, but caſt away the fyrſte water. Alſo there is a Paſney y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſomwhat red, the whiche may be eaten both rawe and ſoden, &amp; with them and Nauewes togyther ye maye make a very good meate, and fayre and red in colour, the which be ſoden as Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neppes be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Plantago.</head>
               <p>PLantago, this is called Playntayne, it is colde and drye in the ſeconde degre.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:41"/>
               <p>¶ The vertue is this, for hedache take Plan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne and bynde it aboute thy necke, and the ache ſhal go out of the heed. Alſo for diſeaſes in the body, ſeth this herbe in good lycoure in what ye wyl, and vſe to drynke it, and it ſhal clenſe the mawe, &amp; the other inwardes. Alſo for hym that bledeth at the noſe, gyue hym to drynke the ioyce of it, and it ſhall ſeaſe lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Alſo yf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the body of any man be wexen harde, ſtamp this herbe with grece and make a playſter of it, and lay it on the hardnes, and lyghtly it ſhalbe ſofte and make it hole. Alſo for bytynge of a ſerpent, take this herbe and drynke it with wyne. Alſo for the dyſeaſe in the mouth, take the ioyce of this herbe, &amp; hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it longe in thy mouth, and ete the leues of this herbe. For hym that may not well pyſſe, ſethe this herbe and drynke it. Alſo for a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten humour in the breſt, and aboute the herte, take the ioyce of this herbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayght of .x. d. and medle it with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and gyue hym to ete a ſponefull at one tyme, and that ſhal ſpurge the breſt. For ache i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fete, take this herbe with vynegre, and drynke it. Alſo it heleth woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, and clenſeth the fylthe out of woundes. Alſo it ſwageth rankelynge, and ſtauncheth the mencions both with drynke &amp; with play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters made with powdre of Armonyake, and
<pb facs="tcp:191753:42"/> of ſankdragone, &amp; barly mele, with the white of egges made in a playſter, and layde to the ſore. For the canker and the payne in the gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, take the ioyce therof and medle it with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and vynegre, and powdre of Alume, and that ſhall ſlee the Canker in the mouthe. Alſo for the feuers ſtamp thre rotes of Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, and tempre it with water, and gyue it hym to drynke that hath the Feuers, and he ſhal be hole. For the Iaundes ſtampe Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and Letuſe togyther, and tempre them with vynegre, &amp; make a playſter therof, and lay it to the ryght ſyde, and vſe it tyll thou be hole, &amp; it is good for the bytyng of an adder, drynke the ioyce of it, and lay the ſubſtaunce of the herbe to the ſore. For the ſame hange the rote of plantayne aboute the necke of the pacye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and meruaylouſly it helpeth. For the potagre, and for the dyſeaſe in the ſynowes, ſtamp the leues of it with a lytel ſalt, &amp; play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it well therto, &amp; meruaylouſly it helpeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Porrum.</head>
               <p>POrru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this is called a leke, it is hote and drye in the thyrde degre, it deſyreth loſe grounde and fat, &amp; well donged, in that they ſhal beſt profyte in hote places and temperat, they may be ſowen in Decembre in temperet places, and colde. They may be ſowen in Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuary,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:42"/> February &amp; Marche, whan the groun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de is well dygged and dyght, and it maye be ſowen by it ſelfe, or medled with other ſedes of herbes in good fat grounde well dygged, and tourned aboue it with good donge, this ſede wolde be ſowen ſomwhat thycke, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be ſomwhat ſpronge, take vp the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt lekes, &amp; plante them in forowes, but take away none of theyr rotes when ye ſet them in the forowes, but when ye ſet them with a dybble cut awaye the rotes almoſte vp to the leke heed, and cut away the vppermoſt of the leues, they may be planted in Iuly, Auguſt, Septembre, and Octobre, they be moche pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytable in Marche, and in Apryll next folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, but in your plantyng you ſhall not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke after fat ſoft grounde, for menely grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that is beſt, and that grounde that is almoſte drye is beſt, there is two maner of ſettyng of Lekes, one is in forowes as is the maner in Bonony, &amp; the forowe muſte be fro the other a ſpa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne large, and the lekes muſt be ſet in the forowe .iiii. fyngers brede eche fro other, and when ye make the next forowe caſt the earth on the lekes, and trede it downe ſoftely with thy fote. The ſeconde maner is thus, when the grounde is well dygged and raked, then make holes with a great dybble, &amp; euery hole
<pb facs="tcp:191753:43"/> fro other a large ſpanne and more, in whiche the lekes muſt be ſet in, but fyl not thy holes, nor put earth on them, but let them be voyde. iii. wekes, when wedes grow amonge them pul them vp, and kepe them clene fro wedes. Dyuers Auctours ſaye that the lekes that be thus planted be better then any other, or they may wellbe planted amonge great onyons, and when the onyons be taken away, wede the lekes and you ſhall fynde them fayre and good, and when ye plucke vp leue ſome in a place, leue ſome for ſede, the whiche ſede may be kept thre yeare, and it be hanged vp in the hulles, lekes be beſt ſoden, or thre tymes waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed before they be eaten. ¶ The vertue is for a wounde, take lekes &amp; ſtamp them wel with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and laye it to the wounde, and it wyll hele it. For the coughe take the ioyce of lekes and vſe to drynke it. For the ſame, take the ioyce of Lekes, and medle it with womans mylke, and vſe to drynke it, and it wyll clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe the longes of all vyces.</p>
               <lg xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>¶ Fracturas ſolidat: duritaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> relaxat</l>
                  <l>Vulnuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> appoſitum: cito cum ſale claudit.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Piretrum.</head>
               <p>PIretrum, this is called Pelleter, it is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and drye in the thyrde degre, the rote is vſed in medycynes, fyue yeare he maye be
<pb facs="tcp:191753:43"/> kepte in his vertue, and knowe ye well that his ſharpnes is not knowen anone, it ſhulde be puned &amp; holden in the mouthe. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is of loſyng, and drawynge, and of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumynge. To make a gargaryſme, take pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leter and fygges, and boyle them in vynegre or in ſwete wyne, and it wyll clenſe the bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of ſuperfluyte of flewme. Alſo yf it be chewed in the mouthe, it helpeth the palſy in the tongue. Alſo for the palſy and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> potagre, ſtampe it and ſethe it in wyne and oyle, and playſter it to the greuaunce, this playſter hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peth moche therfore, yf thou may haue grene pelyter ſtamp it, and lay it ſokynge in wyne xv. dayes, and after boyle it wel and put ther to wexe &amp; oyle, for this is the beſt oyntement for all the foreſayde dyſeaſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Papauer.</head>
               <p>PApauer, this is called Popy, it is colde and dry. There is two maners of them, the wyte Popy is colde and moyſte, and it is good to cauſe one to ſlepe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſede therof well gathered may be kept .x. yeare. ¶ The vertue is of clenſyng, it is put in medycynes with a determynacyon as the ſede maye be receyued of whyte Popy or blacke. For to prouoke a ſlepe, make a playſter of eche of them, or one of them with womans mylke, and the whyte
<pb facs="tcp:191753:44"/> an egge, and laye it to the temples. The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Salerne gaue to yonge chyldren the Popy, but they wolde gyue theym no blacke Popy, for it made them moch heuy. Alſo for a hote poſtume in the begynnynge, &amp; for cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fynge of the lyuer, take the ſede of whyte Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>py, or els the herbe of it, and ſtamp it &amp; medle it with oyle of Roſes, and playſter it to the greuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Alſo for drynes in feuer etyke and in other feuers, take and het<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oyle of vyolet medled with powder of Popy ſede, &amp; anoynt the ſmall of the backe therwith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Polipodium.</head>
               <p>POlipodium, this is called Polypodye, it is hote in the thyrde degre, and dry in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de degre. This Polypody is a ferne that groweth vpon okes, or on walles, or ſtones, but the Polypody that groweth on Okes is the beſt, gather the rotes of it and lay it a day in the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, choſe that is grene, and that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che appereth dry, whan it is broken it is to be refuſed. ¶ The vertue is of dyſſoluynge, of drawyng, of purgynge flewme, and ſpecyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of melancoly, wherfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly he is put in boylyng, and to flewmatyk, and melanco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyous hole men, he is gyuen to preſerue theyr helth, and know well that in the boylynge of Polypody ſhuld be put in ſome thynge to ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clude
<pb facs="tcp:191753:44"/> and put out ventuoſyte as Anyſe ſede, Fenel ſede, for they exclude out moche wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and vnbyndeth humours. Alſo for the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tydyan, and for Illica paſſio, and to kepe a mans helth, do thus ſtamp halfe an ounce of Polipody or an ounce, yf ye wyl haue it mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che laxatyue, than boyle it with prunes and vyolettes in fenell water or anyſe, in a great quantyte, than ſtrayne it and gyue it the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyent at euenyng &amp; at mornyng. Alſo ſtamp it &amp; ſeth it in water with fenell ſede, &amp; make a good brothe therof with a Chekyn therin, with ſwete ſauoured ſpyces, and gyue the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyent to eate. Alſo make a drynke therof af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this maner, ſtamp it and boyle it in wyne and after put more wyne therto, &amp; ſo make vp your drynke with ſwete ſauoured ſpyces.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Pienium.</head>
               <p>PIenium, this is called Pyeny, it is hote and drye in the ſeconde degre, ſo ſayeth Ypocras and Galien the good phyloſophers ſay that the rote therof goth to dyuers medy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynes, and it wyl laſt .x. yere, and it is colde. ¶ The vertue is good for the palſy, drye the rote and drynke powdre with Caſter ſoden in wyne. Alſo the ſame is good for the ſtone. Alſo yf a man be coſtyue and may not go to draught, take and ſtrawe the powdre therof
<pb facs="tcp:191753:45"/> on cotton, and put in to his fundement, and drynke the powder in whyte wyne. Alſo for a man or woman that hath the fallyng euyll, ete it and drynke it in wyne. Alſo hange the rote aboute his necke, and it wyll ſaue hym without doubt within .xv. dayes. Alſo it hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the ſores in the mouth. Alſo yf thou ſeth it in wyne, it helpeth the ſplen. Alſo drynke Pyeny with water and ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and do therto powdre of Colyandre, and this is good for the ſtomacke, for the mylt, &amp; for grauel in the raynes. Alſo it is good for wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for dyuers dyſeaſes, and ſeth it in whyte wyne, and gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a woman to drynke therof, &amp; it wyll hele here blader, and make here to pyſſe the ſtone, and it wyl hele her of the matry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Alſo Pye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſede whan it is blacke, it maketh delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of the bed of the chylde in her wombe, and at euery tyme when ſhe ſhall vſe to dryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke it, ſhe muſt drynke .xv. ſedes at one tyme.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .xv. letter begynneth with .Q.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Quinquefolio.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Vinquefolio, this is called Quynckefoyle, it is colde &amp; drye in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de degre, this herbe is good for ache in a mans lymbes and for ache of the heed, mouth, tongue, and
<pb facs="tcp:191753:45"/> throte that is ſore, take and ſeth this herbe in wyne, and gyue the pacient to drynke therof thre dayes fyrſte and laſt, and he ſhal be hole. Alſo ſtamp it and drynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of it in ale, and it wyll ſeace the akynge and gnawynge of a man or woman. Alſo yf a man blede ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re at the noſe gyue hym to drynke the ioyce of it with wyne, and anoynt his heed well with the ioyce of this herbe, &amp; anone the blode ſhall ſtaunche. For to ſlee a canker, ſeth it in wyne with the grece of a ſwyne, and make a play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter therof, and lay it on the canker, &amp; it ſhall ſlee it. Alſo take powdre of Quynckefoyle, and medle it with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyl and therwith rubbe thy mouth, tongue, throte, &amp; the chekes with in, and it wyl ſpurge it wel. Alſo for poyſon or bytyng of a ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of quynck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foyle, and drynke it with wyne, and meruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly it reſyſteth venym.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .xvi. letter begynneth with .R.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Rybbeworte.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ybbeworte is an herbe that groweth in gardaynes. ¶ The vertue is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feuer quartayne, take the ioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of this herbe, and drynke it two houres before that ye thynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſeaſe
<pb facs="tcp:191753:46"/> ſhal come to you, and by the grace of God it ſhall go fro you. For them that here not well, put in to theyr eres the ioyce, and yf there be any rotten humours it wyll drye them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Rednetle.</head>
               <p>REdnetle is called a palyfe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grekes, it is hote of vertue, for it bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth them that touche it. ¶ The vertue is good for the Iaundes yf it be ſoden in wyne and dronke, it clenſeth the colour meruaylouſly. For the olde coughe ſeth theſedes in water, and put honny therto, and drynke it, and it wyll hele the coughe, and take away the coldnes of the lunges, and ſwellyng of the bely. Alſo vyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre that the ſede of netels is ſoden in is good agaynſt ſcurfe in the heade, yf the heade be waſſhed therwith .ii. or .iii. tymes, and then rynſed with fayre water.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Roſa.</head>
               <p>ROſa, this is called red Roſe, it is colde in the fyrſte degre, &amp; dry in the ſeconde degre, drye Roſes and grene roſes be vſed in medicynes, and of grene roſes be made many confeccyons. Alſo drye roſes be put in medy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynes, when a receyte of Roſes is made, for they be ſoone made i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> powdre, of roſes is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de mell roſet, ſugre roſet, ſyrop of roſes, a lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary of roſes, water of roſes, and oyle of ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.
<pb facs="tcp:191753:46"/> Melroſet is made thus, take fayre pury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, &amp; new red roſes, the whyte endes of them clyped a way, then chop them ſmall, and put them in to the ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and boyle them menely togither, to knowe when it is boyled ynoughe, ye ſhal know it by the ſwete odour and the colour rufe, fyue yere he may be kept in his vertue. ¶ The vertue of the roſes be of comfortynge, and by the ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny he hath vertue of clenſyng. In wynter and in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer it may be gyuen competently to feble, ſycke, fluma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyke, melancolye, and coloryke people. Alſo Mulſa is made of water and mele roſet, and it may be gyuen after the thyrde daye that it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of the bathe. For to clenſe the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke of colde humour, gyue hym melroſet with water that fenell ſede is boyled in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge therin .iii. graynes of ſalt, yf the ſycke may take it, this ſhuld be the quantyte of Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes and honny. In .vii. pounde of ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny put a pounde of roſes. Sugre roſet is made thus, take newe gathered Roſes, and ſtampe them ryght ſmall with ſugre, than put it in a glaſſe and .xxx. dayes let it ſtande in the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, and ſtyrre it well and medle it well togyther, and ſo it may be kept thre yere in his vertue. The quantyte of ſugre and Roſes ſhulde be thus in .iiii. pounde of ſugre a pounde of Roſes, he
<pb facs="tcp:191753:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> hath vertue of conſtraynynge, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of the fluxe in the wombe, take ſugre roſet and powder of maſtyke, of euery one a dragma, and medſe them wel togyther and gyue it to the ſycke, after that gyue hym roſe water that Maſtyke and cloues be ſoden in. Syrop of Roſes is made thus, ſome do take roſes dyght as it is beforeſayde, &amp; boyle them in water, and i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that water ſtrayned they put ſugre and make a ſyrope therof, and ſome do make it better, for they put Roſes in a veſſell hauynge a ſtrayght mouthe, and they put to the roſes hote water, and they let it ſtande a day and a nyght, and of that water puttyng to it ſugre they make ſyrop, and ſome do put more of roſes in the foreſayd veſſel, and more of hote water, &amp; let it ſtande as is beforſayd, and ſo they make a red water, and make ther of a ſyrope, and ſome do ſtampe newe roſes, and they ſtrayne out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of it, and ſugre therwith they make ſyrope, &amp; this is the beſt makynge of ſyrope, and knowe well that ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope made of freſſhe &amp; newe roſes, ſom what meanely they be laxe, in the ende they bynde, but ſyrope made of drye roſes, fyrſte and laſt they bynde. Syrope of Roſes hath vertue of comfortynge, and conſtraynyng agaynſt the fluxe of the wombe, and he vomyte gyue it
<pb facs="tcp:191753:47"/> hym with rayne water, or with Roſe water in a feuer. After lettynge of blode, gyue it to hym with colde water. Alſo the ſame for the ſyncopyne. Oyle of roſes is made thus, ſome boyle roſes in oyle and kepe it. Some do fyll a glaſſe with roſes and oyle, and they boyle it in a cawdron ful of water, and this oyle is good. Some ſtampe freſſhe roſes with oyle, and they put it in a veſſel of glaſſe, and ſet it in the ſonne .l. dayes, and this oyle is good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt chafynge of the lyuer, yf it be anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therwith. Alſo it is good for the dyſeaſe in the heade that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of hete, anoynte the forheed, and the temples with oyle of roſes, the water of roſes hath vertue of comfortyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and conſtraynynge agaynſt the fluxe of the wombe, and vomyte. Alſo gyue hym roſe water to drynke, or elles Roſe water boyled with Maſtyke and cloues, it is beſt agaynſt the fluxe and feblenes of vertue yf it come of a fluxe by a ſharpe medycyne. Alſo roſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is good for the ſyncopyne, and the cardya<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cle, gyue it hym to drynke, and ſpryncle the water on his face, and the water is good for iyes, and in oyntementes for the face, for it taketh away the wembes and the ſuperfluite and ſtrayneth the ſkynne. Alſo dry roſes put to the noſe to ſmell, do comforte the brayne,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:48"/> and herte, and quencheth the ſpyryte. Alſo agaynſt the fluxe of the wombe, and colour, gyue hym roſes boyled in rayne water. Alſo a playſter made of Roſes, and the whyte of egges and vynegre, &amp; dyp a ſponge in it, and lay it on thy mouth of the ſtomacke, agaynſt the Syncopyne, gyue hym to drynke water that Roſes haue be boyled in, and gyue hym powdre of roſes in a rere egge, to make oyle of roſes, take .ii. pounde of oyle, and a pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and an halfe of roſes, and put all in a glaſſe, and put the glaſſe in a cawderon full of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and hange it therin, and boyle it tyll the thyrde parte be waſted, and after ſtrayne it throughe a lynen clothe, and kepe it for your vſe, for this oyle is loſynge, and ſerueth for many thynges. Some do put Roſe water in a glaſſe, and they put Roſes with theyr dewe therto, and they make it to boyle in water, then they ſet it in the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne tyll it be red, &amp; this water is beſt, this hath vertue of comfortyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and conſtraynynge, and for the fluxe of the wombe, and agaynſt vomyte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Roſemary.</head>
               <p>ROſemarye is an herbe that is hote and drye. ¶ The vertue is good agaynſt al euylles in the body, take the flowers and put them in a lynnen clothe, and ſo boyle them in
<pb facs="tcp:191753:48"/> fayre clene water to the halfe, &amp; coole it and drynke it. Take the flowers and make pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre therof, and bynde it to the ryght arme in a lynen cloth, and it ſhall make the lyght and mery. Alſo ete the flowers with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny faſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge with ſowre brede, and there ſhal ryſe in the none euyll ſwellynges. Alſo take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flowers, and put them in a cheſt amonge your clothes or amonge bokes, and mothes ſhall not hurte them, boyle the flowers in gotes mylke, and than lette them ſtande all a nyghte vnder the ayre fayre couered, &amp; after that gyue hym to drynke therof that hath the tyſyke, &amp; it ſhall delyuer hym. Boyle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leues in whyte wyne, and waſſhe thy face therwith, thy berde, and thy browes, and there ſhall no cornes growe out, but thou ſhall haue a fayre face, put the leues vnder thy beddes heed, and thou ſhal be delyuered of all euyl dremes. Breke the leues ſmall to powdre, and laye them on a canker, and it ſhall ſlee it. Take the leues &amp; put them in to a veſſell of wyne, and it ſhall preſerue it fro tartnes and euyl ſauour, and yf thou ſell that wyne, thou ſhall haue good lucke in the ſale. yf thou be feble with vnkyndly ſwete, take and boyle the leues in clene water, and whan the water is colde, do therto as moche of whyte wyne, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make therin ſoppes,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:49"/> and eate well therof, and thou ſhalte recouer appetyte. Yf thou haue the fluxe, boyle the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in ſtronge ayſell, and bynde them in a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen clothe, and bynde it to thy wombe, and anone the fluxe ſhall withdrawe. Yf thy leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be blowen with the goute, boyle the leues in water, and then take the leues and bynde them in a lynen cloth about thy legges, and it ſhall do the good. Take the leues and boyle them in ſtronge Ayſell, and bynde them in a cloth to thy ſtomacke, and it ſhall delyuer the of all euyls. Yf thou haue the coughe, drynke the water of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leues boyled in whyte wyne, and it wyll hele the. Take the rynde of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, and make powdre therof, and drynke it for the poſe, and it ſhal helpe the. Take the tymbre therof, and brene it to cooles, &amp; make powdre therof, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put it in a lynen cloth and rubbe thy tethe therwith, and yf there be any wormes therin it ſhal ſlee them, and kepe thy teth from all euyls. Alſo make the a boxe of the woode and ſmell to it, and it ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thy youth. Alſo put therof in thy dores, or in thy houſe, and thou ſhal be without dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of adders and other venymous ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, make the a barell therof, and drynke thou of the drynke that ſtandeth therin, &amp; thou nedes to fere no poyſon that ſhall hurte the. And yf
<pb facs="tcp:191753:49"/> thou ſet it in thy gardayne, kepe it honeſtly, for it is moche profytable. Alſo yf a man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue loſt his ſmellyng of the ayre, or els he may not drawe his breth, make a fyre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wode, and take his breth therwith, and gyue it hym to eate, and he ſhallbe hole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Ruta.</head>
               <p>RVta, this is called Rewe, this is hote and dry in the ſeconde degre, the leues and the ſedes be vſed in medicynes, the ſedes may be kepte. x. yeare, and the leues a yeare. ¶ The vertue is of purgynge, dyſſoluynge, and conſumynge. For the heedache, take the ioyce of rewe, and hete it, and put it in to his noſe thyrlles, for it ſpurgeth out flewme and clenſeth the brayne, the ioyce ſoden with wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. For feblenes of ſyght, put rewe in a pot with ale, and let the pacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vſe to drynke of it. For ſtoppynge of the ſplen and lyuer, the ſtrangury and the fluxe, ſeth Rewe in wyne with rotes of Fenell, or powdre of rewe with the ioyce of Fenel and drynke it warme. Alſo for an ache or fretyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, ſtamp rewe with powdre of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn, and playſter it to the greuaunce. Alſo agaynſt ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nym, drynke the ioyce of rewe. For bytynge of a venymous beſt or worme, playſter rewe to the bytynge. For feble iye ſyght, ſtyll wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:191753:50"/> of rewe and roſes togyther, and put ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in your iyes. Alſo an oyntement for ſore iyes, ſtampe rewe and fenell togyther of eche lyke moche by weyght, and medle them with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and Eufroſe, &amp; it is a good oyntement for ſore iyes. Take Rewe, Comyn, and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, of eche a lyke moche by weyght, &amp; gryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de them ſmal togyther, and medle them with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny and vynegre, and it is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ache in the breſt, and in the raynes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .xvii. letter begynneth with .S.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Sinapium.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Inapium, it is called Muſtarde, it is hote and drye in the mydle of the .iiii. degre, &amp; not the herbe but the ſede is put in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycynes. Fyue yeare he may be kept i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his vertue. ¶ The vertue is of loſynge, of drawynge, of makynge thyn, and of conſumynge. For the palſye of the tongue, take and chewe the ſede in your mouth, &amp; holde it vnder the tongue, and it ſhal do you good. Alſo for the palſy in other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres, ſeth the ſede in wyne, and laye it to the ſore place, and it is beſt in the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the dyſeaſe. Alſo take the powdre
<pb facs="tcp:191753:50"/> of it, and put it in to your noſe thyrlles, and it wyll make you to neſe, and it clenſeth the brayne, and ſuperfluyte of flume. Alſo ſeth it in wyne and fygges, and holde it warme in your mouth tyll it be almoſte colde, then take as moche more, &amp; do ſo. v. or. vi. tymes a day, &amp; as moche another day, and this is good for an olde poſe of toughe and flumy humour in the heed. Alſo for ſtoppynge of the ſplen and the lyuer, ſeth the ſede in water with rotes of fenell, then ſtrayne it, and put therto honny, and gyue it to the ſycke to drynke. For hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſplen, ſeth the herbe of it in wyne, and playſter it to the greuaunce. For to rype and breke a poſtume, ſtampe this herbe well with hogges grece, and lay it to the poſtume. Alſo for the ſtrangury, take this herbe, and ſethe it in oyle and wyne, and playſter it to the greuaunce, and it wyl loſe it. Alſo for the Ciatica, and for olde ſores, take muſtarde ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and the thyrde parte of cro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of whyte breade, and fygges, ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and vynegre, after as the ache of the ſore requyreth, the more of the fygges and honny, that is there the more ſharper is the ſtrength of the ſede, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more breade and vynegre that is in it, the more we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker is the ſede, but I ſay not that ye ſhall put this confeccyon to all ſores, but to great and
<pb facs="tcp:191753:51"/> olde ſores, his vertue is yf he be eaten, it ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth a mans wyt, it clenſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bely, it breketh the ſtone, it purgeth the vryne, menſtruoſyte and comforteth the ſtomacke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Smalage.</head>
               <p>SMalage is an herbe that groweth in gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daynes, it is hote and drye in the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the thyrde degre, &amp; drye in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. ¶ The vertue is good for col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and wicked humours in the ſtomacke, and comforteth the ſtomacke, the lyuer, and the lunges, &amp; it is good for woundes, take Sma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage ſede, rew ſede, Peper, and ſalt, &amp; grynde them well togyther, and tempre theym with wyne and drynke it. For ranklynges and to ceaſe the brennynge and akynge, &amp; to brynge them to theyr kynde agayne. Alſo it is good to drynke for the feuer tercyan.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Saluia.</head>
               <p>SAluia is called Sage, &amp; it is hote in the fyrſte degre, and drye in the ſeconde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre, the leues onely be taken in medycynes, both grene and drye, he may be kept a yeare. There be two maner of Sages, the garday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and the wylde Sage, yf thou wyll haue Sage for medycynes, take the leues of gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne Sage. ¶ The vertue is it conſumeth more, &amp; comforteth more then the other doth.
<pb facs="tcp:191753:51"/> For the palſy ſeth the leues of Sage i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyne, and vſe to drynke it, for the ſame ſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leues in wyne, &amp; playſter it to the greuaunce. Alſo it is good to put in ſauce, for the ſtrangury, the flux, and the matryce it clenſeth, ſeth the leues in water, and let the pacient ſyt ouer it, and receyue the hote fume of it, and it ſhal do hym moche good. Alſo it is good for venym or poyſon, ſeth Sage in ale or wyne, and vſe to drynke it .iii. dayes, and thou ſhall be hole by the grace of god. For the ſtomacke drynke the ioyce of ſage with water and honny, and it is good to clenſe a mans body to vſe it both rype and grene, it wyll make a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes body clene, therfore who that vſeth to eate of this herbe or drynke it, it is mernayle that any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenyent ſhulde greue them that vſe it. Yf ye haue an ytchynge on you, waſſhe it well with the ioyce of this herbe, and it ſhall ſlee the ytchyng. Alſo drynke Sage with wyne, and a lytell wormwode, and it ſhall ceaſe the ache vnder the ſydes, the wombe, and the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, it is good for the palſy and dropſy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Satureia.</head>
               <p>SAtureia is called Sauery, it is hote and drye in the .iiii. degree. ¶ The vertue of this is it purgeth the body, ſeth it in wyne or water and drynke it, &amp; it purgeth the raynes,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:52"/> the bladder, the menſtruoſyte in the bowels, it purgeth the lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges &amp; loſeth great humours, and compelleth and putteth hym our by the mouth by ſpyttynge, therfore he is brennyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge &amp; ſtyrreth hym that vſeth lechery, therfore it is forbyd to vſe it moche in meates. Soke it in vynegre or wyne, and drynke it, and it ſhall make the haue a meke ſtomacke. Alſo when it flowreth, it ſhulde be gathered and dryed, &amp; powdre made therof. Alſo take the powdre of Sauery, and boyle it with clary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and vſe to eate therof, or boyle it in wyne and drynke it, &amp; it wyll loſe toughe flewme in the breſte. Alſo for fretynge in the bely drynke powdre of it in warme wyne, &amp; thou ſhal be hole. Alſo yf ye take the leſſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uery, it hath the ſame vertue &amp; ſtrengthe that the other Sauery hath. Alſo make grewell with water and flower, and powdre of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery, and ete therof, and that ſhall clenſe all the ſpyrytuall membres of a man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Saxfrage.</head>
               <p>SAxfrage is hote and drye in the thyrde degre. ¶ The vertue is good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone, ſeth the rote of it in wyne, and drynke it. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it is good for the dyſeaſe of colyke and the ſtrangury, &amp; the powdre of it be eaten with an egge, it is good for the ſame. It maye be
<pb facs="tcp:191753:52"/> kept in his vertue. iii. yeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Scabioſa.</head>
               <p>SCabioſa is called Scabias, it is hote and drye in the thyrde degre, to dry it there is no profyte in it. ¶ The vertue is good for the ſcabbes, take the ioyce of it, vynegre, &amp; oyle, and boyle them togither tyl they wax thycke and kepe it for it is good for ſcabbes. For the Emerawdes ſeth them in water, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyt ouer it, and take the fume of it and vſe it, and thou ſhall be hole. Stampe it and ſeth it in wyne, and the drynke is good to dyſtroye humours in the ſtomacke, and drynke it euery daye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge with Euroſe, and thou ſhall be hole, and thou ſhal neuer haue the Peſtylence bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyle thou do vſe it. For the lyuer ſtamp it &amp; ſeth it in wyne, &amp; drynke it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Sothernwood.</head>
               <p>SOthernwood is an herbe that groweth in the felde. ¶ The vertue of it is good for the coughe, and for byndynge in the bely, and in the breſt, and for dyſeaſe in the bones, and good for them that maye not well pyſſe, take the ſede of this herbe and ſtamp it, and drynke it with water, and it is good for all the aforeſayd. Alſo for the dyſeaſes in the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, ſtampe this herbe with betayne &amp; drynke it, and it helpeth well. Alſo for the bytynge
<pb facs="tcp:191753:53"/> of a ſerpent, and for venym, ſtamp this herbe and drynke it with wyne, and it is good. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the colde feuer, ſtampe this herbe with wyne, and drynke it, and thou ſhall be hole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Syngrene.</head>
               <p>SYngrene is colde and moyſt in the .iii. degre. ¶ The vertue of this herbe, &amp; alſo the ioyce of the ſame herbe is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for many dyſeaſes, ſtampe this herbe with grece and playſter it to the dyſeaſe, and meruaylouſly it helpeth. For dyſeaſes &amp; dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes of the iyes, ſtampe this herbe and put of the ioyce in the ſore iyes. For chafynge of the lyner, take the ioyce of it &amp; vynegre, and dyp a clothe therin, and playſter it to the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce. For bytynge or ſcaldynge, make an oyntment of the ioyce of this herbe, and oyle of roſes and waxe, but lay it not to tyll after the thre fyrſte dayes, but fyrſt anoynt it with grece and ſuche other. Alſo for a dyſeaſe of a hote cauſe, this is good to be layde therto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Stytche worte.</head>
               <p>STytche worte or byrdeſtonge, this is hote and moyſte in the fyrſte degre. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is this, it is good to hele ſtytches, woundes, and alſo the ſore iyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Scamony.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:53"/>
               <p>SCamony is hote and drye in the .iii. de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre, the leues onely be beſt in medy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynes, it may be kept a yere in his ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue or two for nede. ¶ The vertue is good for the diſeaſe in the ſtomacke, boyle the leues of it in wyne, and drynke it. Alſo the aforeſayd drynke is good for the bely. For the ſtrangu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and flux, alſo a ſtewe made with boylyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of it in water or wyne, is good for the fore ſayd, yf it be boyled in oyle, and playſter it to the ſame aforeſayd, it is better.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Sene.</head>
               <p>SEne is hote and drye in the .iiii. degre it groweth on the other ſyde the ſee, and moſte about Babilon, the beſt be the flowers and the braunches of it. ¶ The vertue is good for many dyſeaſes, as the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge euyll, for the ſynecop, for the ſplen, for the Emerawdes, &amp; for the quartayne, ſyrope made of it boyled in water, and ſugre is good for all the aforeſayde, ſyrope made with the ioyce of Borage is good for the aforeſayde. Alſo Dyaſcorides co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth to make Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell of the aforeſayde with boylyng of vyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre and ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, &amp; it wyll be good for the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd. And this herbe may be kept .x. yeare in his ſtrength and vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Selondyne.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:54"/>
               <p>SElondyne is hote and drye in the .iiii. degre, &amp; Galyen ſayth that it is good for ſore iyes. ¶ The vertue is good for ſore iyes, take the ioyce of ſelondyne, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rote boyle it well togyther in a pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, &amp; when it is colde anoynt thy iyes therwith. Take ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>londyne and wryng out the ioyce, and medle it with whyte wyne, and anoynt thy vyſage therwith, and it ſhall do away frakles of the vyſage. The ioyce of ſelondyne &amp; gotes don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge medled togyther ſmall in a morter, then yf thou lay it to a canker in a womans pappe, it ſhall ſlee the canker. Alſo take the ioyce of ſelondyne, and powdre of brym ſtone, and me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dle them well togyther, and it wyll helpe to do awaye the morfewe, &amp; ſeth the rote in wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and when the pot is taken down, let hym holde his mouthe open ouer it, that the brethe may go in to his body, and that ſhall ſlee the canker in the mouthe, it is good for hym that hath dronken venym with his owne ſtale, and that wyll ſaue hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Sauayne.</head>
               <p>SAuayne is hote and drye in the ſeconde degre. ¶ The vertue is good to ſlee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in the wombe, and to brynge them out yf it be ſoden in wyne, and gyue to the pacyent to drynke. It is good with butter or grece to
<pb facs="tcp:191753:54"/> make an oyntment for the ſcabbe that re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth to hele it and drye it vp, and it is good for the hedache, yf it be ſtamped and tempered with vynegre, &amp; make a playſter therof, and lay it to thy temples &amp; vpon the molde of thy heed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Scabioſe.</head>
               <p>SCabioſe is colde and moyſte in the .ii. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is good for the lyuer, ſtampe it and ſethe it in wyne. And it wyll dyſtroy wycked humours in the ſtomacke, and drynke it euery daye faſtynge with Euroſe, and thou ſhall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neuer haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume bredynge within the, as longe as thou doſt vſe this medycyne.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .xviii. lettre begynneth with .T.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Townecreſſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ownecreſſes, is hote and drye in the thyrde degre, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de wyll endure good .v. yeare. ¶ The vertue is good to ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the flux and the menſyon, yf thou take the ſede and broſe it in a morter of braſſe, and gyue the ſycke to drynke therof thre dayes euery day a peny wayght at ones with red wyne warmed, &amp; in theſe .iii. dayes he ſhal be ſtaunched, or els he ſhall dye of that euyll, it is good for the palſy, and for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leflanke,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:55"/> take the ſede and ſeth it with wyne and do it in a poket, and bynde it to the ſyde there as the greuaunce is. Alſo it is good for hym that maye not pyſſe, take the ſede &amp; ſeth it in wyne and oyle Olyue, &amp; bynde it to thy ſhare. It is good for a mans fundament that goeth out, yf it be taken of colde, then it muſt be put in agayne, and ſtrawe the powdre on the foundement, thy raynes with ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, and then ſtrawe the powdre aboue with the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre of Comen, or powdre of Calafine, for all theſe be kyndly for it. Alſo take the ſtalkes of Townecreſſes, and bren them, and there ſhal no venymous beeſt, ne worme abyde the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, nor ſmell therof, but he ſhall dye or els flye awaye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Tapſubarbeſto.</head>
               <p>TApſubarbeſto is called Melon, it is col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and drye. ¶ The vertue of it is good for the Emerawdes, and it be ſoden in wyne and ſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med clene. Alſo it is good to waſſhe the greuaunce therwith. It is good alſo for the fluxe in the belye. To prouoke vomyte, take two dragmes of the powdre of the rote of Melon, and drynke it in wyne, and it wyl prouoke vomyte. Alſo the ſedes prouoketh vryne and cauſeth the to pyſſe, and clenſeth the raynes &amp; the bladder of grauell &amp; ſtones.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:191753:55"/>
            <head>¶ The .xix. letter begynneth with .V.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Vyolet.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Yolet is colde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte degre, and moyſte in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde. ¶ The vertue of it is good for a blaſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iyes, take the rotes of vyolettes, and ſtampe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with myrre and ſaffron, &amp; at nyght lay it to the ſore iyes. Alſo for a wounde in the heade, ſtamp the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of Vyolettes with honny and vynegre, and playſter it to the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, and it ſhall hele it. Alſo for them that may not ſlepe for ſycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſethe this herbe in water, and at euen let hym ſoke well his fete in the water to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, when he goth to bed, bynde of this herbe to his temples, and he ſhall ſlepe well by the grace of Gad. Take Vyolettes, Myrre, and Saffron, and make a playſter, and laye it to the ſore iyes that be ſwolen, and it ſhall ceaſe akynge, and bate the ſwellynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Vua ſuauis.</head>
               <p>VVa ſuauis, this is called the ſwete ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyn, it is hote and moyſte. ¶ The ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is of clenſynge, ſcowryng, or ſmothynge. Rayſynges eaten or boyled in wyne is good for the colde coughe. Alſo ſeth them in wyne and they be good to playſter on the colde po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:56"/> and alſo good for the colde ſtomacke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ Veruayne.</head>
               <p>VEruayne, this is hote and drye in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conde degre. ¶ The vertue is good for all maner of euylles of venym, yf the pacyent drynke it tempred with wyne, and ſtamp the herbe, and laye it on euery maner of bytynge of venymous beeſt, and it wyll drawout the venym and ſaue the ſore, who that vſeth it, it wyll make good breth, &amp; do away the ſtynke of the mouth. Alſo who that hath the Feuer tercyan, take .iii. rotes and .iii. croppes of the ſame herbe, and ſtamp them and tempre them with fayre clene water, and gyue it to the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient to drynke. Alſo who that hath the feuer quartayn, let hym take the ſame drynke. Alſo it is good for the ſtomacke, the lyuer, and the lunges. Alſo take Veruayne, Betayne, and Saxfrage, of euery of theym a lyke moche, and ſtamp them with whyte wyne tempred, and this is good for them that hath the ſtone. Alſo they that bere Veruayne vpon theym, they ſhall haue loue and grace of great may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and they ſhall alſo graunte hym his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge, yf that his aſkyng be good and ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, this herbe is hote and drye.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="part">
            <head>¶ The .xx. lettre begynneth with .w.</head>
            <div type="herb">
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:56"/>
               <head>¶ watercreſſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Atercreſſes be hote and drye in the ſeconde degre. ¶ The vertue of this her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be is good yf ye ſethe them in water by them ſelfe, and drynke it, or ſeth it i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fleſſhe and ſup of the brothe, and it wyll clenſe well the inwarde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres. Alſo it is good agaynſt the ſtrangulyon and the fluxe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ wylde neppe or woodbynde.</head>
               <p>WYlde neppe or woodbynde, this herbe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a flower lyke to the hop, &amp; after the flower he bereth a grene bery, &amp; it hath a great roote. ¶ The vertue of this herbe is moſte in the rote, it is good for ſynowes that be ſhronken, or cut to make them ſouple, and to haue theyr owne courſe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr propre kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Go to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rote of wylde Neppe, that is lyke woodbynde, &amp; make a hole in the myddes of the rote, then couer it well agayne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ayer go out, nor y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no rayne go in, nor water, pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre, nor the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne come not to moche to it, let it ſtande ſo all a nyght and a daye, then after that go to it, and thou ſhalt fynde therin a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne lycour, take out y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> licour with a ſpone, and put it in to a clene glaſſe, and do ſo euery day as longe as thou fyndeſt ought in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole,
<pb facs="tcp:191753:57"/> and this muſt be done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moneth of Apryl, or May, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anoynt the ſore with it agaynſt the fyre, then wete a lynen clothe in the ſame lycour, and lap it aboute the ſore, and it ſhal be hole in ſhorte ſpace on warantyſe, by the grace of god. For the gowte a ſouerayne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyne, take the rote of wylde Nep, and the rote of the wylde docke ſoden by it ſelfe, and cut them in thyn peces, and part awaye the vtter rynde, and cutte them in quarters, then boyle them in clene water. ii. or. iii. houres, then ſtamp them in a morter as ſmall as can be, then putte therto a quantyte of ſote of a chymny, and tempre them with the mylke of a kowe that the here is of one colour, then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the pyſſe of a man that is faſtyng, &amp; make a playſter therof, and boyle it togyther, and as hote as ye maye ſuffre it, laye it to the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce a day and a nyght, &amp; ſo do. ix. tymes, and it ſhall, hele the on warantyſe by the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="herb">
               <head>¶ wormwood.</head>
               <p>WOrmwood is hote and drye in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde degre. ¶ The vertue is good for wormes in the wombe, yf it be ſtamped and the ioyce wrong out, and myngled with ſwete mylke, and gyue to the pacye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, and ſethe this herbe in wyne, and make a
<pb facs="tcp:191753:57"/> playſter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wombe, make powdre of worm wood, Centory, betayne, of eche a lyke moch by wayght, and medle all well togyther, and the powdre wyl ſlee wormes in the wombe, both when it is eaten in potage and dronken. Alſo for the mylte that is ſwollen of a colde mater, ſeth it in wyne and let the ſycke dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke therof, and that ſhal hele hym, and make a playſter of the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the herbe, and ſay it all hote to thy wombe agaynſt the greuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. Alſo ſtampe wormwood &amp; tempre it with vynegre, &amp; with toſted ſowre breed grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den therwith, &amp; the ioyce of myntes, and the ioyce of plantayne, of eche a lyke moche, and frye them wel togyther, then make a playſter and lay it to the mouthe of the ſtomacke, and this ſhall ſtaunche brekynge or caſtyng, For wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in a mans eres be it ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or erewygge, take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyce of wormwood, and put it in the ere. Alſo for the dropſye ſeth it in wyne, &amp; gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the ſycke to drynke at mornynge and at euenynge, and it ſhall helpe hym.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:191753:58"/>
            <head>¶ Hereafter foloweth the vertue of the Oken tree.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Oke be .iiij. thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges beſyde the lefe the which be ryghte profytable to the helth of man, that is to wete the Acorne, and the cup that it groweth in, the galles and the lyme. The carnels in powdre be profyta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble agaynſt the feblenes of the vertiuer of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentyfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay agaynſt feblenes of bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and agaynſt the paſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> called diabetican, and agaynſt the ſtrangurye, and agaynſt the ſickenes called diſſenturian, and agaynſt the ſtone in the raynes, and the bladder, and it is good for them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may not holde theyr water. The cuppe of the Acornes is good agaynſt vomytes of colour, and agaynſt neſyng, and it dryeth, &amp; conſumeth flewme in the mouth of the ſtomacke. The gall after the opynyon of Albert, ſo that they be not greatly holowe be good agaynſt the fluxe, and agaynſt ſly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge and ſlypernes of guttes, and agaynſt the flowres of women, and that powdre hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth them of many infyrmytyes. &amp;c. ¶ Alſo by experyence of Gardyners, and planters, the powdre of the gall mynged with honny, perce a hole in a tre, and put it therin, and the fruyte ſhal be blacke. Nowe with the lyme of the Oke, Phyſycyons, and Surgyans do
<pb facs="tcp:191753:58"/> many cures therwith, &amp; of it is made an oynt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment for the palſy, and of a mans yarde, and agaynſt an infyrmyte called deabetan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo therof is made a ſyrop for the dropſy that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of colde called ypoſarco, and it conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth watery humours. And alſo men be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the fruyte of axes quartayne, tercian, and cotidyan. Alſo in the tre is a thynge gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, which women knowe by experyence it maketh them haſtely to be deliuered of chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, which dowche men call it Archemſel, and therof is made bedes. ¶ The laſt concluſyon of this Oken leues, of this leues is diſtylled a water, whiche healeth all the fluxe of the wombe called dyſſentuaryan, lauaryan, and dyaryan. Alſo it is good for the flowers of women, and for the Emeraudes. Alſo this lefe in powdre put in the noſe, ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheth the bledynge therof, and ſpyttyng of blode. Alſo this lefe is holſome agaynſt the ache of the herte, agaynſt the epilacion of the lyuer, and of the ſplen, &amp; agaynſt the neſyng, &amp; agaynſt the coughe, and the heade ache, and agaynſt the ache of the ſtomacke, &amp; the wynde of the ſtomacke, and agaynſt the colyke, &amp; the ache of the wombe, and the fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes, and it breketh the ſtone of the raynes, and the bladder, and alſo women that be colde, it dyſpoſeth them
<pb facs="tcp:191753:59"/> to be able to conceyue, it is holſome to all ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of creatures of all maner ages, &amp; for all dyſeaſes to be taken at all tymes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere. &amp;c. ¶ wherfore ſurgyans knowynge the trouthe leyth Oken leues vpon woundes, and that done they nede none other oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, it heleth all maner of wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, the canker, the fyſtula, and ſaynt Anthonies fyre, a vayne made in the water of the Oke heleth the dropſy, and all ſepourneſſe. Alſo who ſoeuer ones in the weke eteth one of the leues, he ſhall neuer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſtynkynge breth, nor the toth ache, nor pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaccyon in his gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes. &amp;c. nor of his eres.</p>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>¶ This is the makynge of Aqua vite perfectiſſima.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake the rote of Saxfrage, &amp; Parcely, Alyſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, Fenell, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, yſope, Pynyryall, Roſemary, Laueder, Prymeroſe, Mynt, Ori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gan, Sauge, Calamynt, Auence, Bittayn, Saueyn, of eche halfe a quartron, Galynga le, blacke Peper, whyte Peper, longe Peper, Cloues, Nutmegges, of eche an ounce, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel, Maces, Quylybes, of eche two ounces, Setwale, Peletre of ſpayne, tre of Aloes, of eche an ounce and an halfe, and ſtamp thyne herbes, and powdre thy ſpyces, and put them
<pb facs="tcp:191753:59"/> togyther in the wyne, and let them ſtande all nyght, &amp; on the morowe dyſtyl them through a ſerpentory, this water hath many vertues, and it is better at the fyrſte dyſtyllacyon of the Canon, then at the thyrde diſtyllacyon of the Serpentorye. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="procedure">
               <head>¶ To graffe and plante.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O graffe fruyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall haue no core. Take a graffe and bowe it in both endes combyng, and cutte both endes graftwyſe, and ſo faſten them into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtocke. And yf it growe ſo with the tre cutte awaye the great ende, and let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmaller ende growe, and his fruyte ſhall haue no core <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ¶ yf thou wylt graffe dyuers fruytes vpon one ſtocke, that hath as many braunches as thou wylte haue graffes on, and in euery braunche ſet a graffe in maner and fourme as it is ſayde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; euermore choſe thy graffe on the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſyde of the tre that bereth it, and next the top yf you may, &amp; then mayſt thou graffe dyuers fruytes in one clift, but none of them may be thycker the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other as thy reaſon wyll tel the in that workyng. ¶ It is to be noted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graffers ſaye, that euery tre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſet on ſaynt Lambar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des day, ſhall proue and come to profyte.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:191753:60"/>
            <head>¶ Here begynneth the table of this preſent boke.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A.</head>
               <item>¶ Agnus caſtus.</item>
               <item>Apium.</item>
               <item>Auctum.</item>
               <item>Apium riſus.</item>
               <item>Abſinthium.</item>
               <item>Archemeſia.</item>
               <item>Affodillus.</item>
               <item>Aſtrologia longa.</item>
               <item>Abrotanum.</item>
               <item>Aſtrologia rotunda.</item>
               <item>Ameos.</item>
               <item>Alleluya.</item>
               <item>Agrimonia.</item>
               <item>Auancia.</item>
               <item>Altea.</item>
               <item>Amariſta.</item>
               <item>Aniſum.</item>
               <item>Alleum.</item>
               <item>Aſtarton.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>¶ Betonia.</item>
               <item>Balſaminta.</item>
               <item>Beta.</item>
               <item>Borago domeſtices.</item>
               <item>Bigula.</item>
               <item>Burneta.</item>
               <item>Burſa poſtoris.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>¶ Camamilla.</item>
               <item>Calamintum.</item>
               <item>Craſſula maior.</item>
               <item>Craſſula minor.</item>
               <item>Cituca.</item>
               <item>Centuaria maior.</item>
               <item>Centuaria minor.</item>
               <item>Carin.</item>
               <item>Celodonia.</item>
               <item>Cidamum.</item>
               <item>Cauſis.</item>
               <item>Cortandrum.</item>
               <item>Capillus veneris.</item>
               <item>Crocus.</item>
               <item>Centinodium.</item>
               <item>Caprifolium.</item>
               <item>Canabaria.</item>
               <item>Coſtus.</item>
               <item>Cepe.</item>
               <item>Columbina.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:60"/>
               <item>Cominum.</item>
               <item>Cardiaca.</item>
               <item>Ciſera.</item>
               <item>Camelion.</item>
               <item>Conſolida maior.</item>
               <item>Conſolida minor.</item>
               <item>Conſolida media.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>¶ Dragancia.</item>
               <item>Diptanum.</item>
               <item>Daucus aſinius.</item>
               <item>Daucus creticus.</item>
               <item>Dens leonis.</item>
               <item>Dragancia feminea.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>¶ Elena campana.</item>
               <item>Endiua.</item>
               <item>Eruca.</item>
               <item>Eufragia.</item>
               <item>Ebulus.</item>
               <item>Edera.</item>
               <item>Edera tereſtris.</item>
               <item>Eborus.</item>
               <item>Eſabrus.</item>
               <item>Epatica.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>¶ Famula.</item>
               <item>Fumus terre.</item>
               <item>Fragra.</item>
               <item>Fabaria maior.</item>
               <item>Filex.</item>
               <item>Filipendula.</item>
               <item>Feniculum.</item>
               <item>Faxmus.</item>
               <item>Finiculus porcinus.</item>
               <item>Febrifuga.</item>
               <item>Filago.</item>
               <item>Flammula minor.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>¶ Granum.</item>
               <item>Geneſcula.</item>
               <item>Genciana.</item>
               <item>Galanga.</item>
               <item>Granum ſolis.</item>
               <item>Gladiolus.</item>
               <item>Gracia dei.</item>
               <item>Gracia dei maior.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>¶ Herba cruciata.</item>
               <item>Herba chriſtofori.</item>
               <item>Herba walteri.</item>
               <item>Herba Roberti.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:61"/>
               <item>Herba martis.</item>
               <item>Haſtula regia.</item>
               <item>Herba Iohannis.</item>
               <item>Herba Petri.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>¶ Iuſquiamus.</item>
               <item>Iſopus.</item>
               <item>Ireoſe.</item>
               <item>Iris.</item>
               <item>Iua.</item>
               <item>Iacia alba.</item>
               <item>Iaſia nigra.</item>
               <item>Ippia maior.</item>
               <item>Ippia minor.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>¶ Laneſticum.</item>
               <item>Lingua ceruina.</item>
               <item>Lilium.</item>
               <item>Liguſtrum.</item>
               <item>Lingua bouis.</item>
               <item>Lingua Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis ma.</item>
               <item>Lingua Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis mi.</item>
               <item>Lingua canis.</item>
               <item>Lingua hircina.</item>
               <item>Lupinus.</item>
               <item>Labrum veneris.</item>
               <item>Lauendula.</item>
               <item>Lactuca.</item>
               <item>Lactuca ſiluatica.</item>
               <item>Lactuca leporica.</item>
               <item>Lollium.</item>
               <item>Laparium rubeum.</item>
               <item>Linum.</item>
               <item>Lauriola.</item>
               <item>Licoriſa.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>¶ Millefolio minor.</item>
               <item>Mercurialis.</item>
               <item>Menta.</item>
               <item>Menta romana.</item>
               <item>Malua.</item>
               <item>Morell or nyght ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe.</item>
               <item>Maſtyke.</item>
               <item>Magerum.</item>
               <item>Millefolium maior.</item>
               <item>Motherworte, or</item>
               <item>Mugworte.</item>
               <item>Maces.</item>
               <item>Menta.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>¶ Nux muſcata.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:61"/>
               <item>Napo.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>¶ Olibanum.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>¶ Plumeus.</item>
               <item>Piper.</item>
               <item>Pympernell.</item>
               <item>Pulegium.</item>
               <item>Pencedamum vel Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niculus porcinus.</item>
               <item>Petrocilium.</item>
               <item>Peritorium.</item>
               <item>Plaſtinaca.</item>
               <item>Plantago.</item>
               <item>Porrum.</item>
               <item>Piretrum.</item>
               <item>Papauer.</item>
               <item>Polipodium.</item>
               <item>Pienium.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q</head>
               <item>¶ Quinquefolio.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>¶ Rybbeworte.</item>
               <item>Rednetell.</item>
               <item>Roſa.</item>
               <item>Roſemary.</item>
               <item>Ruta.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>¶ Sinapium.</item>
               <item>Smalege.</item>
               <item>Saluia.</item>
               <item>Satureia.</item>
               <item>Saxfrage.</item>
               <item>Scabioſa.</item>
               <item>Sothernwood.</item>
               <item>Syngrene.</item>
               <item>Stytcheworte.</item>
               <item>Scamony.</item>
               <item>Sene.</item>
               <item>Selyndyne.</item>
               <item>Sauayne.</item>
               <item>Scabioſe.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>¶ Townecreſſes.</item>
               <item>Tapſubarbeſto.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>¶ Vyolet.</item>
               <item>Vua ſuauis.</item>
               <item>Veruayne.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W</head>
               <item>¶ watercreſſes wylde neppe or woodbynde.</item>
               <item>wormwood.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:191753:62"/>
               <item>¶ The vertue of the Oken tre.</item>
               <item>¶ The Oken lefe.</item>
               <item>¶ The makynge of Aqua vite perfectiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</item>
               <item>¶ Graffynge &amp; plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶ Finis Tabule.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted by me Robert wyer, dwellynge in ſaynt Martyns pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe, at the ſygne of ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Euangelyſt, beſyde Charyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge Croſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Wyer: McKerrow 69</figDesc>
                  <head>ROBERT WYER.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:191753:62"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
